<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fancies ague-fittes, or beauties nettle-bed Wherein, one nightes lodging, will cost nine monethes nettling. Handled in sixe discourses, pithie, pleasing, and profitable. Patere, aut abstine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00546</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114626</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15023</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00546)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15023)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 790:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fancies ague-fittes, or beauties nettle-bed Wherein, one nightes lodging, will cost nine monethes nettling. Handled in sixe discourses, pithie, pleasing, and profitable. Patere, aut abstine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Simson for William Iones, dwelling at Holborne conduit, at the signe of the Gunne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Six essays on beauty and love.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-I K⁴ (K4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Fancies Ague-fittes, Or <hi>Beauties Nettle-bed:</hi> Wherein, one nightes lodging, will coſt nine monethes Nettling.</p>
            <p>Handled in ſixe Diſcourſes, pithie, pleaſing, and profitable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Patere, aut abſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G. Simſon</hi> for <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling at Holborne conduit, at the ſigne of the Gunne. 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Maſter <hi>William Baſſet</hi> Eſquire, one of her Maieſties Iuſtices of the peace, in both the Counties of Derbie and Stafford, Likewiſe, to the moſt vertou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman his wife: all health and happineſſe moſt hartily wiſhed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ebtes, of what antiquitye ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, are not by delay diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, neither promiſes, by long protracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, impeached from performance. How iuſtly both theſe (right worſhipfull) appertaine to me, though happilie out of date in your too long expectation: I may be ſory for no ſooner compaſſing, and you in fauour wil I hope receiue what comes at laſt, excuſing all errors with
<pb facs="tcp:15023:3"/>the common addage, better late then neuer. When your worſhip was high ſheriffe of <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> as ſome-way to expreſſe thankfulneſse, for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours then founde, I promiſed you, that in ſuch forte as this I would ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſalute ye. But being hindred by a long ſickneſſe, as alſo conuenient meanes to diſcharge my promiſe: I could neuer till this inſtant be ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, as to greete you with any thing woorthie your viwe, or ſufficient to plead the leaſt parte of performance. And though my conceite heerof may be greate, yet how you ſhall thinke therof may well be doubted, becauſe oppinions are as varyous, as mens hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours are diuers: yet the ſound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe I haue in your euer-affable na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, makes mee hope, that the meannes of my gift, ſhall be ſhaddow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:15023:3"/>with the intire depth of great good will, and what wantes in this, in ſome other heerafter will be better ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Nor ſeek I to be free from my former bond of promiſe, by this ſillie trifle, in reſpect of ſo great deſeruing: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that your worſhip would take this onward, to arme ye with ſome hope of attayning to the reſt, and that withal to expreſſe, I am willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue yours in dutie, till the very vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt be diſcharged.</p>
            <p>Both this, my ſelfe and what elſe remaynes in me, I intreat your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip kindely to conſter on, for you ſhal finde them readie on the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to vſe them. In meane while, praying for all happie bleſsings to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and follow you, as alſo the moſt vertuous Gentle-woman your wife, whom heauen enritch with bleſsed
<pb facs="tcp:15023:4"/>ſight of her hopes ioy: I humbly commend ye both to his protection, who hath hitherto had care of you, and will euermore comfort you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:4"/>
            <head>The Argument of each <hi>ſeuerall diſcourſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>Of Beautie. Diſ. 1.</item>
               <item>Of Loue. Diſ. 2.</item>
               <item>Of the meanes to compaſse fauour and acceptaunce. Diſ. 3.</item>
               <item>Of the conſiderations of Loue Diſ. 4.</item>
               <item>Of Iealoſie. Diſ. 5.</item>
               <item>Of the paſſions of Looue. Diſ. 6.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:5"/>
            <head>Of Beautie. The firſt diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Knowe not if among thoſe benefits beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon the body, beauty deſerue to haue any ſuch account made of it, as we do, of halth, agilitie, ſtrength, and diſpoſition: becauſe Beautie is not any thing at all felt by the perſon indued there with, neyther ſerues but to ſuch as ſee it, and to them whom it giueth delight. Now to know, if by Beautie there doth enſue any commoditie, the queſtion is proble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall, and may be debated as for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue, ſo likewiſe for the negatiue, for it appeares, that nature beſtowing beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on any, did it to make them beloued, and that which poſſeſſeth the hartes of men, may be good right be termed migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and drawes all ſortes of commodities to it, not hauing neede of any thing in
<pb facs="tcp:15023:6"/>the protection of others. Briefely, it is well knowen, what good thoſe famous courtezanes got by it, as <hi>Flora, Layis, Lamia</hi> and their like, moreouer, it is neceſſarie we ſhould remember, that Beautie is ſuch a gift of nature, as all the gold in the world cannot giue vs the like; for eloquence, ſcience, and gentilitie, are attayned only by ſtudie and diligence.</p>
            <p>If then no ſmall eſtimation be to be made of the fauoure, good grace, and loue of men; we muſt confeſſe Beautie to be a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, at leaſt the cauſe thereof, in winning and procuring vs ſuch frendes. But when (on the other ſide) I conſider, that thoſe frendes which are followers of Beautie, be rather louers of their owne pleaſures and voluptuouſnes, ſo that they loue not indeede the beautifull body, but better may be called enemies, yea traitours to the honor and good renowne of Beautie, then any true freendes or well willers: I reſt in my former oppinion, and dare not repute beautie to be a benefit.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:6"/>
            <p>VVhen likewiſe I call auncient hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to memorie, I finde how hurtful beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was to <hi>Lucretia,</hi> albeit ſhe was moſt chaſt and vertuous, to modeſt <hi>Suſanna,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and diſcreet <hi>Penelope,</hi> mirrours and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of perfect loyaltie: both they and an infinite number of their like, had bene moſt happie, if their beauties had not beene ſo much coueted and deſired.</p>
            <p>In like manner I conſider, that ſuch as are followers of beautie, haue no reſpect but of their owne paſſions, and no care at all of beauties reputation, becauſe if beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in ſome ſorte doth bring commonditie to ſuch as are adorned therewith, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to commaund mens goodes at their pleaſure: yet can they not for all that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule their harts and willes, for many times they giue their goods away to enioy their pleaſure, and they that yeeld thereto, make ſale both of their bodies and honor, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themſelues to baſe proſtitution onely for monye. Such women therefore cannot iuſtly terme themſelues miſtreſſes
<pb facs="tcp:15023:7"/>when to haue a little power of their goods, they make their owne perſons as ſeruantes to me, ſo for the bare title of Lady of their money, they make men Lords of their affections, nay, of them ſelues ſo much as may be. We may now ſee if beauty be a benefit to ſuch as delight ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, when it cannot be in her that is indued therewith, becauſe ſhe can neyther feele or ſee it any way, and in trueth, I may here ſpeake as <hi>Epicurus</hi> did of pleaſures, when one demaunded of him, whether pleaſure were a benefit or no, and he thereto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this anſwere; that he hath but little wit, who when his finger is in the fyre, wil aſke of other if he feele payne or no, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fire be hot, and Ice cold: meaning thereby, if a delight be pleaſing to a mans own ſelf, why ſhould he queſtion whether it be a benefit or no, ſince himſelfe both feeles and makes experiment thereof. In like manner I ſay, that he who hath a fayre wife, knowes well if he haue delight or pleaſure, for were not beautie expected
<pb facs="tcp:15023:7"/>and deſired, it would not be ſo generally ſought and purchaſed, which makes mee to coniecture, that a man hauing a fayre wife or friend, eſteemes beautie for a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and cheifeſt pleaſure, and therefore <hi>Plato</hi> giues no other definition of loue, but that it is a deſire of beautie, as very am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply he deliuereth in his dialogues called <hi>Phoedrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this matter therfore, the teſtemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſo many Poets ſhall ſuffiſe mee, who expreſſe in their writings, that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally beautie hath beene magnified, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and honoured, as a great gift of God, and, but that I finde beautie to be enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronned with many perillous diſcommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, I ſhould conſent with them in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. But I conſidder that which many great perſonages haue done before me, of whom I could alledge authorities moſt notable, which might ſerue to ſatiſſie the greateſt loubters; only I wil rehearſe the reaſon that hath moned them to ſuch ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in declaring the reaſon, none can
<pb facs="tcp:15023:8"/>contradict me, but that the proofe is cleare and apparant. For if I ſhould auouch but the alegation of Poets, it myght the be ſayde, that they ſpeake according to their<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> paſſions, and women might refect them as their aduerſaries and enemies to their ſex, whereas if I ſhow the grounded reaſon themſelues may then receiue blame in not giuing credit thereto, or els they dare not tearme themſelues reaſonable when they will giue no place to reaſon.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt then I ſay, that beautie hath this diſcommoditie, it is coueted by euery one, it is moſt hard to be kept and defended, being a thing ſought after by ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (as it were) continually beſieged. For as a garden that is repleniſhed with all faire flowers and fruites, or a treaſurie ſtored with riches moſt precious, is in dayly dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and needeth eſpeciall guardance: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch and no otherwiſe is the beautie of women.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt reaſon alledged by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, whereto they further adde, that beauty
<pb facs="tcp:15023:8"/>begetteth in women great pride and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet-weening, as <hi>Ouid</hi> in this verſe teſtefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faſtus ineſt pulcris, ſequiturque ſuperbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> formam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beautie makes women to bee wonderous proude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In beeing then ſo proud and loftie min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they imagine that their beautie ſhould ſerue them to ſome end or purpoſe, and ſay, that beautie had not bene giuen them, but both they muſt and ought to make ſome vſe of it. And as we note one loue to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get another, ſo do we likewiſe behold, that a woman often ſolicited if ſhe be not ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and ſtrong in reſiſtance, ſhe is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to make ſhipwracke of her beautie, by thoſe entiſings which her beauty procured.</p>
            <p>Perhappes ſome will denie, that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſubiect to loue any other then their huſbandes, but then they muſt confeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15023:9"/>withal that they are apt therein to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, eſpecially if they be indued with admirable beautie, yea many tymes it comes ſo to paſſe, that ſuch beautie hath bene verie hurtfull to their huſbands, and extended to the loſſe of their liues. The example of <hi>Vrias</hi> may ſerue, the huſband to <hi>Berſaba;</hi> but if we ſhall neede any more allegations, it is too well knowen how da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mageable <hi>Hellens</hi> beautie was to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Menelaus,</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Deiphoebus,</hi> who loſt their liues, and made the earth drunke with effuſion of their blood.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe as euident, that which is written of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who had a fayre wife named <hi>Sara,</hi> and becauſe he went with her into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> he ſayd; thou art fayre, and if it be knowen that I am thy huſband, I ſhall be ſlayne, that they may enioy thee, it will be beſt therefore to call me thy brother. Afterwarde, when <hi>Abimelech</hi> ſawe her, <hi>Abraham</hi> was conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to denye he was her huſband. The hiſtorie of <hi>Gyges</hi> and <hi>Candaulus</hi> is as nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:15023:9"/>with infinite others that might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. All which notwithſtanding, I will not ſay as ſome haue doone.</p>
            <q>Cumque pudicitia rara eſt concordia forma.</q>
            <q>Beautie with chaſtitie is ſildome found.</q>
            <p>For I can proue them liers by number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe examples, of very beautifull and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladies, that haue and yet liue in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to this day amongſt vs, and ſo ſhall do for euer, to their confuſion, who haue ſo ſhamefully ſlaundred them.</p>
            <p>But for confirmation of my former ſpeeches, that womens beauties is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to their huſbandes, I will not let ſlip in ſilence, what wiſe <hi>Bias,</hi> a man ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned ſpake, ſaying: Beautie much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and gazed at, is no aſſurance to the huſband, for though vertue be conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned therewith, yet is the man in euident danger, wherefore, the very wiſeſt haue beene of this opinion, that ſuch beautie as is moſt requiſite in women, is to be indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently fayre, or as we ſay in Latine, <hi>Stata
<pb facs="tcp:15023:10"/>forma, aut vxoria forma.</hi> They adde more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, ſince beautie is a thing which decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and weareth old by time, that it is more yrkeſome to him, who hath ſeene his wife beautiful, to note her now depriued there of, and diſpoiled of that flower, euen as the trees of their leaues in winter.</p>
            <p>In like manner can I aſſure ye, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the declaration of ſuch as are not purſued and followed, but by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt and ſhameleſſe: yet beautie is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer alone, but often tymes accompanied with many good graces, and my reaſon is, that we vſually ſhewe our ſelues to others, as they declare themſelues towardes vs, and the beautifull beeing imbraſed, and wel wiſhed by all: ſhewes themſelues like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reciprocally ſsweece, curteous, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable to all. But perhappes you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſome faults vnto me, as making them ſelues proude, when they heare one praiſe or reprite them to be fayre. Such haue no deſert to hold place with honorable dames, becauſe the more vertue is extolled, the
<pb facs="tcp:15023:10"/>more humble it makes the perſon endued therewith.</p>
            <p>I wall ſay, as an anncient and great perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage councelled young Ladies in his time, to veiw themſelues diuers times in a glaſſe, to the end (quoth he) that finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues fayre, they ſhould endeauour to be as beautifull in their mindes, ſhaming that their bodies which are vile and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, ſhould be more goodly then their ſoules, which are deuine and immortall. In like caſe, if they deſcerne themſelues to be foule and miſhapen, they ſhould labour to recompence that difformitie by their good mindes, and ſuch goodly graces as beſt beſeemeth them.</p>
            <p>Such ought to be the dayly practiſe of thoſe which are fayre, becauſe it ſeemes a thing very odious, to ſee a beautifull body not adorned with good graces and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, which want procureth great greife in many beholders, pittying ſo fayre a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhould be in ſuch ſorte blemiſhed, where others are quite contrarie, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:15023:11"/>ſerue leſſe loking on. Therfore, when ſuch ſhall requeſt fauour at mens handes, well may they in ſcorne and deriſion be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that their owne imperfections makes them not regarded, and ſo they continue chaſte, becauſe none cares for them.</p>
            <p>It is the nature of a woman, the more one importunes her, the leſſe ſhe regardes what ſhe would gladlieſt haue, which makes them to obſerue it as a general rule, to deſpiſe them moſt that chiefeſt ſue to them: for the loue which they beare to them ſelues, hinders all loue els they ſhould beſtowe on others, then which there can be nothing more contrarie to loue, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this <hi>Philaftia,</hi> ſelfe loue, or vayne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our ſelues. But I mind not here to to alledge thoſe inconueniences, becauſe the argument would haue but a bad foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, only I ſay, that if a wife addict her ſelfe to loue any one, it is not in regard that her ſelfe is fayre, but becauſe ſhe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teems him faire whom ſhe loues, for we ſee the hard fauored to be as amorous, &amp; ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:15023:11"/>vpon termes to be intreated, as they that are fayreſt, and beſt may brag of beautie. Wherfore it is a thing moſt certaine, that nothing els but the fayre forme of the countenaunce, the beautifull cullour and pleaſing looks of yong perſonages, ſuch as are in the only flower of their age: is that which doth attract affection, ſet open the windowes of good opinion, and by little and little kindles the fire, which afterwarde breakes into loues cheifeſt flame.</p>
            <p>Now many tymes it happens, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers (through the folly of their parentes) ſtriuing to quench this affection and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by force and without reaſon, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els aduantage themſelues thereby: but growe into more trouble, as conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with ſmooke, whereas if they would giue them head or libertie, before ſuch wretches as are lewdeſt and moſt voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they would ouer throw them in their owne naughtineſſe.</p>
            <p>Hereby may we then perceiue, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:15023:12"/>loue ſhould make ſuch perſonages gen: tle kinde and affable, to them which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent their companie, it turnes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, making them melancholique, fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and out of all order. Then let vs not maruaile, why our elders deſcribed loue to be inconſtant and variable, or like to the ſunne, which dayly ſeemes to quench it ſelfe, and yet euery morning renewes his light agayne: for this is my conceite of loue, that as it is mortall and periſhable, ſo it cannot be conſtant in one and the ſelfe ſame kinde.</p>
            <p>But to come to the concluſion of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed, concerning Beautie, I will conclude with <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that of two vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous women, the one beeing fayre, and the other hard fauoured ſhe which ſurpaſſeth the other in beautie, ſhall be more pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and eſteemed then the other can be. And the like may be ſayd of two perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages vertuous and wiſe, the one beeing rich, the other poore: moſt certayne is it, that the rich man ſhall be in more account
<pb facs="tcp:15023:12"/>then the poore, becauſe the one will be more contented then the other. But if beautie or riches ſhall neceſſarily bring their vices with them, then I wil conclude otherwiſe. Orif any one will obiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, that he hath occaſion of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, eyther by beautie or riches: then wil I like wiſe anſwere him, that he hath the more neede of vertue to make reſiſtance.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:13"/>
            <head>Of Loue. The ſecond diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>LOue hath bene of all men ſo extolled &amp; eſteemed, that antiquitie made a god of it, as being the moſt forcible paſſion in vs, to wit, the only cauſe of all our actions. It was not then without reaſon, that they of elder time did ſo worthily celebrate the ſame, and that not onely men ſubiected themſelues thereto, but the Gods likewiſe were vnder loues controlement.</p>
            <p>And not to vſe but this argument one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to ſhewe how it is combined with our ſences, and that it is the efficient cauſe of whatſoeuer we do: in mine oppinion may be deemed ſufficient in this caſe.</p>
            <p>All our actions are to ſome end or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> expreſſeth, to ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant good; why then you will confeſſe, that each one is amorous and deſirous of
<pb facs="tcp:15023:13"/>that end, purpoſe and apparant good, then conſequently whatſoeuer is doone, is done for loue: for eche man looues and deſires that which is his, becauſe he thinks it good, profitable, and needfull for him, as the couetous man, he is amorous of his riches, the enuious, of his reuenge, the inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, of his beaſtly pleaſure, the vertuous: of his vertues, and conſequently, each man doth frame and leuell all his endeuours, to the end of pleaſing him ſelfe, which ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or more <hi>Plato</hi> giueth vnto it.</p>
            <p>I will not here trouble my ſelfe in collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting anthorities from our elders, who haue ſo highly exalted the powre of loue, only I muſt ſay, that there is no paſſion in vs more ſtrong and piercing, as may be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them that affect and loue honor who dare boldely oppoſe their liues agaynſt the cannons mouth, as valiant enemies and diſpiſers of death: others for the looue of their Miſtreſſes, to doo ſuch things as elſe were impoſſible, euen deſperate hazard of their goods and liues</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:14"/>
            <p>Now herein make I no iote of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betweene the loue which a man beares to a woman, and the loue he caries to any goodly thing: for I ſtand vpon thoſe tearmes of definition, which <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe hath giuen to loue, namely, that it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to enioy whatſoeuer is beautifull. For I call that beautie, which a man thinkes to be good, and (as he in the beginning of his <hi>Ethicques</hi> calles it) the apparant good, which is the end of al our actions. Likwiſe <hi>Plato,</hi> ſpeaking of this beautie diſputes it ingenerall, as the beauty of a vertuous man is nothing els but his vertue: which (ſayth <hi>Cicero</hi>) if it appeare to the eyes of men, we may eaſily preſume, how louely it makes him to them that beholdes it.</p>
            <p>But to particularize this matter, we will ſpeak of the loue of man toward a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and then muſt we ſay in trueth, that it is a thing ſo naturall, as there is no neede of other proofe, ſeeing by common ſence we vnderſtand &amp; call that naturall, which by nature is as vſual to beaſts as men.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:14"/>
            <p>And therefore let me ſay of him that feeles not this paſſion, as a Courtezane did of one which made loue to her, who ſhewed himſelfe ſo cold and dull in his amorous blandiſhmentes: that though (quoth ſhe) I haue moued many men, by much leſſe kindneſſe then I haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to thee, yet I finde all this fauour loſt which hath beene beſtowed on thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou appeareſt to be no man, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a hard and inſenſible ſtone.</p>
            <p>And verily the phiſitions doe ſhew by the anotamie of our bodies, that a man being compoſed of fleſh, blood, and his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther partes, muſt neceſſarily be ſubiect to the humour wherewith he is borne: as he is to yeeld to hunger, thirſt and other appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, which pertake with the diſpoſition of our blood. <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Hermaphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus,</hi> that is both man and woman, ſayth, that man at the firſt was made both male and female, which ſemes to haue ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with others holding the ſame opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But man (ſaith he ſone after being
<pb facs="tcp:15023:15"/>deuided into male and female, hath euer ſince had the appetite of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyning &amp; cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mting himſelfe togeather agayne, (as we diſcerne by deſire of kiſſing imbraſing, &amp; ſuch like,) as he was at the firſt created.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> telles vs an other reaſon, which ſeemes more true and likely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the vnion whereof <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeakes, is not to be ſo agayne conioyned, neyther can man likewiſe haue any hope thereof. He ſayth, that for the conſeruation of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſex and kinde nature hath giuen a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of ingendring, as wel by men as beaſts. Hereof may we ſay, as <hi>Cicero</hi> doth in his booke of olde age: that man ſowes, plantes, grafts, buildes, leaues his bookes for his poſteritie, not bauing any thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing him hereto, but that nature would haue all thinges preſerued in the kinde, wherein firſt of al ſhe brought it into the worlde.</p>
            <p>And this is an influence as common to beaſtes as men, iſſuing from the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of nature, as hunger and thriſt is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:15023:15"/>to man as well as beaſtes, to the end he ſhould maintayne his body, which takes alteration by euapored noriſhment, and deſireth continuall: new fomentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo hunger mſtructeth man when is meete time to feede himſelfe.</p>
            <p>But leaue we this loue or indignation naturall, which rather is beaſtly then hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and let vs ſpeake of that loue, which addreſſeth it ſelfe to the minde, when a man loues a fayre perſon, wiſe and of good grace. And to ſpeake ingenerally of beautie, it ought to be as well vnderſtood of the minde as the bodie: for one is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous of the minde, to acknowledge in the other perſon, ſomewhat or other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with our nature, ſuch as is liking and agreeable with vs Now to know what ioy one minde hath of an other, we may anſwere, that as one bodie is glad of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodie, ſo one minde of an other, ſo the fruition &amp; delight is in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſimpathized. Then he that loueth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that the thoughts of his mind, may v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb facs="tcp:15023:16"/>&amp; ioyne themſelues with the thoughts of the perſon beloued, and as the body of the one receiues the others bodie in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall pleaſure, ſo the minde might meete with another minde, and giue it ſelfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, as in communication of hartes, ſo of willes, ſeruing one anothers vſe, and taking on eyther part a mutuall concord in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and no greater delight can be ſpoken of, then when one findes himſelfe as well beloued, as he doth loue. This may we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcerne, in that God deſireth our loue of vs, vrging it to be giuen with all our hart, by reaſon (on his behalfe) he loues vs infinitely: we muſt then confeſſe, that pleaſure goes before loue, which is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light conceiued in the minde, as he which deſires the pleaſure of a woman, apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in his mind and imagination the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light he is to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oy, and ſo ſometymes, as if he had performed it, is he pleaſed &amp; ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatiſfied, which is the thing that we call to loue.</p>
            <p>In like manner, he that loues a vertuous
<pb facs="tcp:15023:16"/>body, deſires to be in her good grace, and ſo reciprocally to be beloued. Behold then wherin the benefit of loue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth, nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any aſſigne other cauſe of the good which is felt by delight of the mind, then that we find of our ſelues, which makes euery man well borne, deſire to be reputed, eſteemed &amp; loued of euery one, eſpecially the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loueth &amp; reuerenceth, as of his prince, of honorable gentlemen, and al his other wel willers beſide. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe it happeneth often times, that when one ſpeakes of loue, we rather vnerſtand the loue which a man beares to a woman, then that which one man caries to another: ſo may I well ſaye, and that by good right, a man loues a woman more then he can doe any man whatſoeuer, for there is no one but will confeſſe, that two cords or ſtrings binde and hold more ſtrongly then one can do. If then it be ſo, this muſt neceſſarily be likewiſe graunted, that man and woman beeing ioyned together in body and minde, their loue is more firme
<pb facs="tcp:15023:17"/>and ſtrict, then that of man to man can be, beeing lincked together but in minde onely. Yet will I not denie for al this, but that a ſtable and firme bond is found in one mans minde to another, for their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: if then the vertues in a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not ſuch, as may anſwere and agree with them in her huſband, then doubtleſſe I muſt confeſſe, that the loue betweene men is much more great, then the other of a man toward a woman.</p>
            <p>But in equallitie of vertues, I ſay a man loues a woman better then he can doe a man, becauſe man is not a mind onely, nor a bodie onely, but a mind and bodie ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned togeather, and while the mariage of the minde to the bodie indureth, there is ſuch ſocietie betweene them, that the one ſuffers the others infirmitie, reioyceth and pertakes in contentment or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>It appeareth then, that the mind depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth altogether on the bodie, as is playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted, becauſe the bodie is the organe
<pb facs="tcp:15023:17"/>and inſtrument of the mind, and as the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of man looſeth it ſelfe, when the veſſell of the brayne is offended or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: ſo likewiſe doth iudgement and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence, for we ſee there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene a foole and a wiſe man, but the health &amp; diſpoſition of the braine and not of the minde, as the minde being made of one and the ſelfe ſame matter, but performing their functions by the bodies organes.</p>
            <p>So we ſee, that a man diſtempered by wine fuming vp into his brayne, becomes like a foole or a frantique man: then here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by may we well perceiue, that there is a agreat ſimpathie and coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betweene the minde and the bodie, wherevpon, I conclude the loue of men toward women to be great, when the minde and bodie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and meete together by coniunction.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ſome will ſay, there is not found ſo great amitie betweene a brother and ſiſter or kinſman, as with her that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyeth more pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>te ſocietie: euen ſo the
<pb facs="tcp:15023:18"/>delight is better agreeable, man being no no way participating of any thing, then by meanes of the bodie. And if we ſhould neede to produce diuinitie, we know that God requires aſwel the ſeruice of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as of our mindes, the ſacramentes are applyed to the body aſwel as to the mind, and the body aſwell as the minde, muſt participate (after this life) of good or euill in the other world, in briefe, without the body, a man were not a man, neyther could be capable of knowing any thing: which may be gathered by the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our common ſence, wherto all the other ſences apply themſelues and that by ſight, hearing, and the other as helpers, the ſoule receiues enſtruction, which ſight, &amp; hearing being taken from man, he is then no other but as a brute beaſt &amp; inſenſible.</p>
            <p>But it is true, that I make great difference betweene the delight of loue in a beaſt, and the other propper in a man, for that in a beaſt, it goes no further then the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, with out any more matter, and is not
<pb facs="tcp:15023:18"/>moued but by nature onely to ingender, but man hath the delight of the minde and did ſuch pleaſure of the body ſerue to no other end, but to expreſſe the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the minde, yet were it as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as our ſpeech to be an inſtance of our thoughtes, neyther can a man declare his good will and intents, but by the miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the mouth, and other ſignes of the body. In like manner, the greateſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made apparant by kiſſes, mutuallim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracings, and other apt inſtances of the body and I dare affirme, that the man which truely loues, neuer findes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the body ſo pleaſing, as when he ſees his Lady (on her behalſe) dehuer like teſhmonie of her loue to him, and that with a cheareful hart ſhe entertaineth him, which makes a man take more pleaſure in her he loueth, and by whom he is beloued agayne, then in any other whatſoeuer, be ſhe neuer ſo beautifull.</p>
            <p>For (as ſaith one, and very well too) when a man receiues a preſent from a Lord, he regardeth not the gift, how faire or rich ſo
<pb facs="tcp:15023:19"/>euer it be, as he doeth the good will and courteſie of the giuer: ſo God acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth not our preſents, neither careth for them, but our intents and good wils only. Therefore we may ſay, that when a man ſporteth, the pleaſure of the body likes him not ſo well, as that of the hart: for if plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be had againſt the good will of any, it ſerues not to him as anye contentment. Contrarywiſe, although he delighted but his body only, yet if he were aſſured of the others good liking, it would ſuffiſe, being loued againe as himſelfe dooth loue.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if it be granted, that the body is in ſuch ſort eſpouſed to the minde, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with the other, it cannot be but an extreame paine, if they delight not one in the other: why then it would ſeeme moſt hurtfull to them, if they ſhould be forced to abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ioy ſo vehement, or abide ſeparation thorowe conſtraint, not daring priuatly or publikly be ſeen together: who ſo thus offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, or ſeeketh to force nature, cannot auoide falling into great danger.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:19"/>
            <p>Why then I muſt ſay, that ſtrict and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire amitie, cannot long continue between a man and woman, without the delight of the bodie, if amitie be bred of one and ſelfe ſame will, not able to endure ſiniſter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries: why then ſuch parties ſhall as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie command and vanquiſh their paſſions, as they receiue good by being in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſight. and harme when they may not be ſo together, or as during not to ſpeake but before witneſſes. This is the reaſon, why loue is ſaid not to continue long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a man and woman, except it be in ſuch as are tyed by the bands of mariage: for betweene others it cannot be, either without great danger, or without ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſcandale, eſpecially ſuch ſecrecie and communication, as is required in loue, which makes of two hearts one, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them inſeperably together.</p>
            <p>As for others, becauſe our lawe giues vs a conſcience, if kindnes be had, hardly can it be durable: but betwene maried perſons, becauſe the wiſe haue made a vertue of
<pb facs="tcp:15023:20"/>neceſſitie, alliaunce is more certaine, to wit, more laſting, hauing made a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and ſocietie together, of all fortunes whatſo uer good and bad.</p>
            <p>But concerning loue, it is very hard to be demeaned with a woman, if ſhe be not his wiſe or freend in delighting: becauſe nature inuites vs to thoſe imbracings and ſecrecies, which follow one another in ſequence, not to be named among ſuch perſons as intend to liue chaſtely. And this I ſpeake, becauſe diſcourſing now of loue, I meane not amitie, which I reſerue for man to man, or brother to ſyſter, or a ſonne to his mother, which cannot well name it ſelfe to be loue, neyther the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre of beauty, diſtinct and ſeperated from amitie and good will: for in trueth, the focietie among amourous perſons is ſuch as the body is but a meane of vniting the ſoules, and heere vpon diuers I hiſitions diſcourſing, haue made a communication of the complexions, taken from the braine, the heart, the lyuer, and in breefe from all
<pb facs="tcp:15023:20"/>the animall partes in man, the lyfe of an inſant being diſpoſed and formed therby, which is the cauſe why men are heere ſo mooued &amp; prouoked wheras other beaſts enter as by a kinde or violence: And hence proceedeth the paſsions of the amourous, expreſſed ſo liuely by Poets both Greeke, Latin, Italian, and others beſide auncient and moderne, eſpecially when they haue ſet downe nothing, but hane evther felt or experimented the ſame ſufficientlye in themſciues. ſo that it is very needfull, if a man will make reſiſtance, to vſe ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, as we read the moſt holye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did, who led their liues in the ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie deſerts, and heere I might alledge what they haue written, but that it is ſuſſicient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye knowne already.</p>
            <p>But all this notwithſtanding, I ſet it not downe as a generall rule, that a man cannot loue a woman but in this manner, and for the delight before rehearſed: for well might I be aſhamed thereof, beſyde, I ſhould doo iniurye to infinite honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:15023:21"/>and chaſte looues. But I ſav, that keeping the one and other from following has na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, therein conſiſts the paine and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſince (as I lately ſpake) the moſt holye perſons being in the wildernes, liuing on fauage rootes, puniſinng their bodies with hard garments, drinking water, and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping little, but lying on ſharpe ſtones, in breeſe, not admitting any remedie: yet haue they in ſuch ſerte beene aſſaulted, as they in theyr writings haue been conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to expreſſe it.</p>
            <p>Now concerning our ſelues, who are trained and brought vp in ſofte and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate manner when we haue perticuler and priuate conference with her whome we beſt looue, being fayre and gracious, and requiting vs with loue: if we could then ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, the glory would be found the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by how much the payne and reſiſtance was difficult, checfely, when in regarde of the affection we beare our freend, we feare to vrge any thing might be vnhonorable. And heerein may the power of looue be
<pb facs="tcp:15023:21"/>diſcerned, which making the louer forget his pleaſure, defrauds his deſire, to content her in al he may whom he ſo dearly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. Of ſuch loyal freends are many to be found, whoſe louers haue had ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie ouer them, as, being vertuous, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſiue reaſon they let paſſe the pleaſure, for the great daunger which followes and enſues thereby.</p>
            <p>His guide herein, as in all thinges elſe is, that the action of a man is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his election, and the election betweene two goods, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is ſayde, a man for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure leaues the following of honor, which is but the minde of a cowardly ſouldier or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aile like houſe keeper, timorous to follow the renouned exerciſe of warre: where contrariwiſe, the braue Souldier, beeing iealous of his honor, beguiles him ſelfe of his eaſe, and the pleaſure he takes in his houſe with his wife, making the hard field his bed, mountes on the ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partes, ſhuts himſelfe into a towne, where he ſuffers extremitie of famine, makes his
<pb facs="tcp:15023:22"/>body a wall agaynſt the cannons batterie, and doth all this for the loue of his honor.</p>
            <p>In like ſort can I ſay, that he which tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loueth, will abſtayne from his owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, be it but to ſatiſfie the chaſt and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt inclination of his beloued. As ſhe likewiſe that lookes for anſwerable looue to her owne, will endeuer by al meanes ſhe can deuiſe, that the grace of her mouth, namely her breath and ſpeech, may beſweet pleaſing and agreeable to her louer.</p>
            <p>But as for ſuch as are vnited by the bonds of marriage, they remem bring the induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their former loues, &amp; how they laboured by al courſes, to congratulat one another in al chaſt and cordiall kindnes: ſo much the more ought they to vphold their coniunction, &amp; heedfully haue an eye from the very beginning, to ſhun all occaſions of diſcention and diſcord; as conſidering, that pieces of wood greenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bined together, will be diſioynd and miſplacd by the leaſt occaſion in the worlde: but contrariwiſe, when the ioynts are well knit and aſſured
<pb facs="tcp:15023:22"/>by long proofe of time, hardly can they be ſunderd, or ſeperated again by force or fire. And as we ſee ſtrawe doth eaſily take fire, ſo may it as quickly be quenched again, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome ſudden matter be added to help and mantaine it: euen ſuch ſhould we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the loue of new maried folks to be, which is not kindled but by the heate of youth, eſpecially the ſweete beauty of the body: ſo that it cannot be firme or durable, if it be not grounded by conformitie of good and honeſt manners, which begets a riciprocall affection of one to the other. Now as for ſuch as cannot endure the firſt frowardnes &amp; riotes of their new matches: I may properly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare them to thoſe, that deeme a raiſin grape like to another, becauſe perhaps before they ſaw vergis made of it. And ſo concerning the new married, who diſdain their huſbands at the firſt meetings they do neither more or leſſe, then like him that becauſe the Bee ſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him a little, caſts away the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity of hony which ſhe then left in his hand. Al things therfore, eſpecial
<pb facs="tcp:15023:23"/>as concerne our affections, ought to be common in marriage, and contrariwiſe, all outrages and iniuries to be vtterly bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>For if <hi>Cato</hi> depriued a Romane Senatour of his office &amp; dignitie, becauſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his daughter he kiſſed his wife, (which in mine opinion was ſentence too ſeuere:) what imagine you ſhould be done to ſuch as offend, iniurie and ſtrike their wiues, Say ſhe be hard fauored &amp; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, it is leſſe praiſe to kiſſe, embrace and toy with her in companie, then the ſhameis reputed greater, to ſtrike, abuſe, &amp; miſtear me her, be it neuer ſo ſecret or how ſoeuer, and this hath bene the fault of very many, as I could make knowen by ſundry examples.</p>
            <p>The delight of loue and beneſit thereof, according to the opinion of the wiſeſt; conſiſteth in foure things: <hi>viz.</hi> ſight, ſpeech kiſſing, and feeling, which is laſt of all and though each of them doth merit a moſt ample diſcourſe, yet he that would know
<pb facs="tcp:15023:23"/>their ſeuerall particularities: let him ſearch the Poets, who haue al ſpoken like moſt ſkilful maiſters, likewiſe let him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the Philoſophers, and among the reſt, <hi>Plato</hi> in his <hi>Conuiuium,</hi> where very largely he hath ſet downe his minde, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue they written liberally hereon, but proued the force of loue, &amp; witneſſed the ſame by their owne endured paſſions.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt and ſecond poyntes, they are the two ſences, wherby all knowledge enters into a man, to wit, ſight and hearing, and it ſeemes that our ſoule taketh her forme by theſe two ſences, for whoſoeuer is depriued of them, hath no difference at all from a brute beaſt. The Philoſophers talke of a common ſence at the beginning of our brayne, whereto all the feeligs of the fantaſie do addreſſe themſelues, &amp; ſo doth iudgement and memorie likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Loue then beget teth it ſelfe by the eyes, which are the gates whereby our conceites do enter &amp; they drawe our inclination ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their iudgement, raiſing a deſire
<pb facs="tcp:15023:24"/>which is called loue, appoynting it to the manſion of the hart, which is the reaſon, that in loue we talke ſo much of the hart: not becauſe the hart is an onely member that hath life, but in regard of the ſoule, which woorks not but by the organes and inſtruments of the hart, conuaying all our other partes to the hart, as the httle fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger cannot ſtirre it ſelfe, but by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the hart, and the hart by our will, which principally abydeth therein.</p>
            <p>Why then, when the eye hath brought to our common ſence the ſigure of beauty, fancie (who is neareſt neighbour to our common ſence) is immediately moued, and ſendes a meſſage thereof to the hart, which foorth with deſires delight and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of that, which to him appeareth ſo beautifull. Now concerning hearing, it likewiſe greatly helpeth loue, for commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the mindes together: for the beautie of the minde conſiſteth in reaſon, which by ſpeech imparteth it ſelfe vnto vs, and hearing carieth all things from the
<pb facs="tcp:15023:24"/>ſence common, to fancie and iudgement, imprinting ſo much in the memorie which afterward ſucceedeth, as prouokes both deſire, appetite and will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Virgill</hi> hath moſt excellently deſcribed, how <hi>Dido</hi> became amorous of <hi>Aneas,</hi> ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that hauing heard of himſelfe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and famous deedes, as alſo what daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers he had eſcaped: his height of valour (which he ſeemed to haue made good proofe of) by little and little entred her minde and opinion, and vrged her to this induction by her ſelf. It is not poſſible, but he muſt needs be deſcended of very good place, for a villaine neuer could performe ſuch enterpriſe: his vertue, his race, and al elſe ſo much moued her, as in the end ſhe was caught faſt in the ſnaries of loue.</p>
            <p>Vertue, beautie, and honeſtie are the true allurers of loue, and therfore <hi>Terqum</hi> was not ſo much mooued with the beauty of <hi>Lucrece,</hi> as her chaſtity &amp; honeſt demeanor, finding her well exerciſed &amp; buſied in her houſe, not idle &amp; ſlothfull as he had done
<pb facs="tcp:15023:25"/>many other, amidſt their pleaſures, bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets and vanities.</p>
            <p>Comunication and ſpeeche declare what a man is, his wiſedome and learning is not knowen but only therby: now knowledge is in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the thing which beſt ſitteth their honor, and wherby they game moſt the loue and fauour of men There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpeech (by good right) is moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitem loue, to teſteſie how &amp; what a manist for it is written, that <hi>Soerates</hi> ſeing a han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome young youth, ſayd to him; Speake, to thee &amp; I may both ſee and know thee. Next vnto ſpeaking is placed kiſſing, and truely, if the pleaſure were not felt which enſueth therby, my ſelfe would deeme it ſtrange, why there is ſometime ſuch for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearaunce from kiſſing, and why we loue rather to kiſſe ones mouthe, rather then any one thing as faire and ſweet: but expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rience teacheth vs, that eſpecially among the reſt, kiſſing is a great parte of delight, a mother kiſſeth her ſon, a brother his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and in Fraunce it is moſt cömon, be
<pb facs="tcp:15023:25"/>cauſe it is counted as a ſaluting, chiefely when one comes from any farre place. Some ſay, that the minds doo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate therby, and haue written wonderfull mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of kiſſes: but what is knowen by ſence, hath no need of further proofe; as when we ſee a thing black or white, it is vaine to de maund any other proofe; when we handle a thing hard or ſoft; when we heare a ſound lowd or lowe; when we taſt a thing ſowre or ſweet, in al theſe other reaſon is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired And ſo ſay I of kiſſing, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to demaund if it be pleaſant or no, for in kiſſing it maketh proofe of it ſelfe, &amp; ſo much the more, becauſe we touch the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom we kiſſe, the pleaſure is great, &amp; then is the benefit refered not to the bodie only, but to the minde: witneſſe thoſe kiſſes which men in times paſt gaue to one another, the father to the ſoune, and the mother alſo, apſayne demonſtration of courteſie and kindneſſe.</p>
            <p>I will unſiſt no other pointes then are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, but leaue them as reſerued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
<pb facs="tcp:15023:26"/>perience, for many thinges are therby done honeſtly, which are not to be named, and many things like wiſe might be named, which were better to be kept in ſecret: as <hi>cicero</hi> ſaid to the ſeuere and ſtoicall iudges, and becauſe it dependeth vpon the ſence. Now to know what is the cauſe of loue, as alſo by what bayts and allurementes he ouertaketh himſelfe: this may not wel be diſcourſed ingeneral, neither am I of their opinion, that ſay a conformitie and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance procureth loue betweene vs: for we haue ſcene the difformed loue the fayre, the ignorant the wiſe with admiration, the infirme and weake magnifiyng hardy and valiaunt men. Briefly, what ſo is faire, what ſo is vertuous, generally in all, at all tymes, and in all places, is praiſed &amp; eſteemed, &amp; that which is vice, is by the vicius the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues reproued. It were an abſurd thing then to ſay, that loue enſueth by reſemblance, and as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayth (reciting the authority of <hi>Euripides</hi>) the earth deſireth rayne when it is drye, the ſicke the Phiſition. True
<pb facs="tcp:15023:26"/>is it, that it is another manner of matter, the amitie which reconciles it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene perſons of ſelfe ſame complexion and inclynation, then in other caſes, and the reaſon is euident: namely, as he that loues an other for his vertue, is likewiſe in ſelfe ſame manner beloued of him againe, if he be vertuous. He that loues a woman for her beautie is loued agayne reciprocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by her, becauſe he hath the like perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and then is it tearmd amitie between perſons, when loue is mutual and in equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; not when an hard fauoured or bad complexyoned man, loueth a fayre and gracious Gentlewomen, for there may be loue in him, but none in her: euen ſo loue (not being actiue and paſſiue in theſe two kindes) is not amitie. To giue then the reaſon of loue, it behoueth to conſider the complection, humour and affection of eyther partie, for I am of this mind that no other but mutual loue can be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted betweene beautifull perſons: but then we muſt conſider, that beauty in a woman is
<pb facs="tcp:15023:27"/>gentleneſle, ſweeteneſſe, affabilitie, and a pleaſing diſpoſition; beautie in a man, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, dignitie, valour, wit, and dexteritie in vertue, thus the beautie of eyther, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly appertayning to the ſex. So ſome do ſay, that if gentleneſſe and beauty in a woman pleaſeth a man: valour, vertue and wiſdome in a man, liketh a woman, which conduceth to the permutation and moſt auncient contract among men.</p>
            <p>In like manner, to make a generall rule of affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in men or women, it is impoſible, becauſe ſo many men ſo many ſeueral ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and complexions. One loues a blacke eye another a gray, in briefe, one ſayth, and that moſt truely: Loue maketh more ſtore of faire women found out, then their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie confirmes them to be amiable or woorth deſiring onely through our owne purſuing of vulgare actions, which each one tearmes his beſt apparant good, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he followes and adicts himſelfe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, although very diuers and vnlikely. This makes ſuch abundance of frowarde
<pb facs="tcp:15023:27"/>natures, and is the fountayne of all teares, ſighes, complantes and greeuances among them that loue, forcing them to ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and violence on them ſelues, that not teares alone, but blood is ſluiced foorth, euen in the middeſt of their deſperate ſiginngs and complaintes.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which enſueth, becauſe they that loue are not ſo pleaſing in their louers eves, as they appeare to them, neyther find they like enterchange of will, but quite contrary. I or while they agree together, delight is equally imbraced, as if a hard fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured man affect a fayre woman, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence his want by comly demeanour, valour and wiſdome: here hence enſueth the onely nouriſhment of loue, when to delight and pleaſe a mans choiſe, he becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth gentle, debonaire and vertuous, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayth in his <hi>Conuiuium,</hi> and <hi>Boccace</hi> likewiſe witneſſeth, deciaring the hiſtorie of ruſtical: <hi>Cynon,</hi> a clowne and badly nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured by nature, yet to compaſſe the fauour of a Lady which he loued, in ſhort while he
<pb facs="tcp:15023:28"/>became ſo ciuill gentle, conformable, valiant and renowned, as no one could equall him in all graces and good partes beſeeming a Gentleman.</p>
            <p>And though loue ſerud vs for nothing els, but to encourage and ſpurre vs onward to vertue, yet were it worthy al praiſe and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatiö. And to approue that it doth ſo, how many hiſtories haue we which teach vs, that loue hath beene the cauſe of vertue and gentlenes, in ſuch perſons as haue don reuerence therto? I referre my ſelfe to the wiſe and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning decei: of the <hi>Tuſcanes,</hi> who declared a ſinguler kindneſſe to their huſbands, in making hazard of their liues for them. For they beeing taken and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon by them of <hi>Sparta,</hi> where they were kept very ſtrictly, to trie if they could conuince them by certaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted proofes, in thoſe matters wherof they ſtood acciſed: they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes to viſite their huſbands in priſon, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayling ſo effectually with their keepers, that they admitted them entrance, only to
<pb facs="tcp:15023:28"/>and ſalute their huſbands. When they were within the priſon, they cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> celled them to put off of their owne garments, and being clad in theirs, they ſhould iſſue forth mour ning and hyding their eyes, in ſigne of grief, according as they hadentred to them, which beeing done, the women remained there ſhut vp in their ſted, ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer what ſoeuer was mean: againſt their huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bands, whome the keepers let ſcape, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe imagining, but that they were the women.</p>
            <p>See now how on the one ſide, ardent affec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion found ſufficient help in need, but for the other parte, let vs not paſſe in ſilence the loyaltie of theſe men, in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the good and kindneſſe thus receiued by their wiues.</p>
            <p>For beeing thus got out of priſon, they went preſently and engirt the mount of <hi>Tangeta,</hi> rayſing the inhabitants &amp; neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring people to take Armes, entring into an open rebellion. Which they of <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> fearing, ſent a herald to them, by whom
<pb facs="tcp:15023:29"/>they grew to ſuch a concluſion: that their wiues were reſtored to them, with monye and their goods beſide, as alſo diuers other aduantages. This example may ſerue for a mirrour of cordiall and vehement loue in women toward their huſbands, and the like in men toward their wiues.</p>
            <p>Let no man then diſcourage himſelfe, how much foeuer he be diſgraced by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or for tune: for there is no hart ſo hard but may be moued in time to pittie, and may by ſeruice merit very much, if no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes were left him of deſert. And truely if the hart contayne any ſparke of vertue it will neuer be ingratfull, or lacke acknowledgement of good will and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe receyued: but will recompence if (at leaſt) with fauour and affabilitie.</p>
            <p>It is true, that (to come to the laſt poynt of delight) it is not onely very hard, but likewiſe impoſſible to gayne any thing, but by ſuch graces as doe ſubdue the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of women, albeit ſome hold opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that obſtinate purſuit, and continuall
<pb facs="tcp:15023:29"/>batterie is ſuch, as there is no Cittie how ſtrong ſoeuer, but will ſubmit therto at laſt, ye the gayne ſo gotten, equals not the harme which then hath no helpe. And therefore I would adurſe ſuch as are in this caſe, to conſider fuſt their owne qualities, then of their miſt reſſes, the tyme &amp; place, which are neceſſarie circumſtances. For when a man ſhall happen to loue a lady, if ſhe exceede him in nobleneſſe of houſe, he ſhould thinke with himſelfe, that it is as great folly in him to imagine he can preuaile, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in him who would catch at the Moone with his teeth. If his miſtreſſe be ſuch, as taking aduiſe by his glaſſe, he ſhall thereby be councelled, not to pretend any thing to her: then he wil conſider likewiſe, whether there be ſuch matters in him ſelfe as may recompence the graces he beholds in her, not ouerweening himſelfe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, for he ſhall ſuffer what he deſerues, and reape as he is regarded. A man ought likewiſe to be ſo diſcreet, as to vſe tyme
<pb facs="tcp:15023:30"/>apt and meete for his purpoſe, and as the place ſhall agree with his miſtreſſe: aboue all, to haue a ſpeciall regarde of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and humour, that he may ſerue according to her appetites: otherwiſe, he ſhalbe like them that but loſe their labour, and become ridiculous, in aſpiring hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then doth beſeeme them.</p>
            <p>If their be any ſo infortunate, that they cannot compaſſe what they would, whereby to reach the heyght of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes: let me ſende them to <hi>Ouids</hi> leſſon in his remedy for loue, ſhunning the place and ſuch occaſions, minding other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres or (as one ſayth) driuing out one nayle with another, and ſuch other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as are there to be found.</p>
            <p>For there is not loue ſo forcible, but time will weare it out, by reaſon at firſt it was engendred by Idleneſſe: then may a man follow other important occaſions, which more dooth concerne his owne good and honour.</p>
            <p>But contrarywyſe, if hee ſee that time
<pb facs="tcp:15023:30"/>may ſoften her rigour: let him beare him ſelfe ſo wiſely in all his behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that he receiue no croſſe through his owne indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. Thus much I deeme ſufficient to be ſayde of Loue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:31"/>
            <head>Of the meanes to compaſſe <hi>fauour and acceptaunce.</hi> The third diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>THe onely thing which makes mee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that ſuch as meddle with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of loue, do fayle in many matters, is, becauſe the more part are often euill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, &amp; then publiſhing abroad the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, refuſall, and hard vſage ſuſtayned by their miſtreſſes, doth but diuulgate their owne defects, and the ſmall or no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert remayning in them. For if they were ſuch as might merit entertaynement, they would not be in ſuch extremities, as dayly they are to be ſeene A diſeaſe is apparant, but the cauſe thereof being not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, makes the remedie to ſeeme impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: therefore let vs immitate the diſcreet Phiſition, who firſt dilligently enquiring of the hurtfull humour, the ſourſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:15023:31"/>ill, his progreſſe, and the qualitie of the perſon; then applyeth what is moſt need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and takes away (by the contrarie) the cauſe of the annoyance.</p>
            <p>To know that then, which makes a man ſo repulſed, and giues him likewiſe accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, (being to ſome the greateſt payne, to other the beſt pleaſure in this world) may ſeeme a matter very hard to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood: for a man may not diſcourſe a thing ingenerall, which is knowne but in perticular, and is likewiſe as diuers, as the circumſtances are contrarie, euen as one receipt may not be giuen to all kindes of Feuers, becauſe they are not of one ſalfe ſame condition.</p>
            <p>Gladly would I learne of Ladies, how a man ought to carrie himſelfe in loue, by what meanes he might inſinuate into their good graces, how he may be moſt welcome to them, and briefely, which way he may ſooneſt pleaſe them: according as <hi>Horace</hi> ſpeaketh of one, who was to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne diuers perſons neare him, one for
<pb facs="tcp:15023:32"/>one taſte, another for another, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould conforme himſelfe to each ones appetite. Neuertheleſſe, becauſe that which is good &amp; honeſt of it ſelf, ſeemeth no other to all, in all places and at all times, ſeeing that which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable to al, doth naturally teach vs what is vice, what is ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, euen as may be ſaid by right of nature: therefore euery one may purchaſe to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, thoſe things which beſt may make him beloued. True it is, that many thinges do change of themſelues, becauſe the relliſh of men are diuers, and in regard that which is good at one tyme, is reproued and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned at another: herein then let vs ſay with the wiſeſt, there is a right way in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which neuer changeth, for reaſon is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore reaſon, and trueth, trueth.</p>
            <p>Ther is another way that is tearmed poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, which concerneth onely ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, meanes and enſtructions, to mayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne this firſt way of nature: but that varieth &amp; chaungeth of it ſelfe, according to the occurrences and occaſions, as dooth
<pb facs="tcp:15023:32"/>the faſhion of garements, the defence of armes, and ſuch like matters. So may we ſay, that vertue is immoueable, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſuch as it hath beene: but the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, thing as ſpeach, the countenaunce, grace, cloſe conceites, and other perticuler matters, muſt be vnſterſtoode according to the perſons, tyme and place, which are the circumſtances, whereby each man ought to iudge of his affaires, leaſt he fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch offence as the ill aduiſed often do.</p>
            <p>VVhy then we will deliuer, what all men ingenerall ſhould haue, and what in perticuler each man ought doe: for, to be in fauour with people ingenerall, he muſt haue that which is generally eſteemed, and the regard which a man makes of one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon onely, begetteth loue; the one neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily preceeding, and then loue following, which proues it ſelfe by the diſinition of beauty, being indeed the deſire of beauty.</p>
            <p>Now this beautie is not onely taken for that of the face, but it conſiſteth likewiſe of the minde in women: beautie appeareth in a well adorned countenaunce, a comely
<pb facs="tcp:15023:33"/>ſweete grace, pleaſing language, breefely, it hath ſuch amorous geſture and behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as ſteales a mans hart that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to note it. The beauty of a man is knowledge, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, a valiant hart, wiſe ſpeech, manly behauiour, and not effeminate.</p>
            <p>This beautie then is but a gift of nature, both in the one and the other, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it lyes not in vs to be beautiful, which makes the more vnskilfulnes in giuing any precept, except prohibition of belying thoſe imperfections which we haue, with practiſe to ſupply what is beſt beſeeming vs; as in ſome to ſpeake grauely, others more ſtearnely, needes no great wit to him who hath ſtudied for it: wheras when one finds himſelfe diſfauoured by beauty, he cannot brag or boaſt but ſtand like one diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And this a thing which iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe, according to our knowledge in theſe caſes more or leſſe, and as matters in themſelues are beſt ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing to vs: for there be ſome which only take pleaſure in things done publiquely when as to others
<pb facs="tcp:15023:33"/>it is the greateſt diſcontentment in the worlde.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe ſerues the fable of the Aſſe, who perſeruing the dogge playing with his maiſter, leaping on him with his feete, and putting his head betweene his his hands: imagined in his groſſe braine, that if he did the like, it woold be as well accepted and liked. Wherevpon, one day after he came to his mayſter, thruſting his feete in his face, and leaping on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: his mayſter ſuppoſing he was fallen madde, commaunded him to haue ſo many good baſtanadoes, as he might fit and repent his forwardneſſe at leyſure: thus ye may ſee how it happens to ſome, who neuertheleſſe (perhaps) had a good intention.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is not to be publiquely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perted: Such a Gentlewoman permitted ament kiſſe her, let him giue hr a greene gowne, and doe other thinges belonging to ſocietie: whereas if another ſhould intrude himſelfe to do ſo much, it might
<pb facs="tcp:15023:34"/>be taken in very bad part, albeit ſhe were not offended with the other.</p>
            <p>Familiaritie often tymes is hurtfull to ſome, as when men take pleaſure in doing ſuch thinges, which notwithſtanding are vnfitting in others, ſometymes by long &amp; priuate frequentation one with another: for it wholely doth depend vpon the will, whether ſhe be contented therwith or no, the abſolute power of liking conſiſteth in her. If one will preſſe forward by ſiniſter meanes to compaſſe her fauour: in ſteed of pleaſing, he puts him ſelfe an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred parts the further off. Beſide, if a man be thought by ſome to be ſcant gracious, ill nurtred, vnworthy ſocietie with perſons of honor; yet by others (happily) he is not ſo reputed for ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times a man hinders his owne adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by not obſeruing time and apt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as when he dallies with women o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wantonly before men of reſpect, or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his follies in a place not fit for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or taketh a woman in an vnhappie houre, in all which there are many that mightily offend. There are ſome houres
<pb facs="tcp:15023:34"/>better then other, and (as one ſayeth) the ſhepheardes houre is moſt perril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; when ſometimes the moſt pleaſanteſt woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, finds her ſelf to be cold in diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; very hardly acquaintable.</p>
            <p>But to preuent this fault, it is neceſſarie to obſerue time, the place, and perſon, by ſlender approches, as, a little and a little, to trye our fortunes: to the end that if a man receiue no profit at all, yet he may auoyd ouer much mocking or deluding of him ſelfe. For, by refuſal of a kiſſe, or other more priuate offers, may be vnderſtood, that he ſhal not do wel in preſuming any further, eſpecially in ſuch caſes, which (as it were fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one degree to another) deliuereth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: ſound aſſurance to a man: &amp; this I dare ſay, that he who growes careleſle of this precept, ſhall but harme his owne content, and do himſelfe vnrepaireable wrong. For it is leſſe diſhonour to a man to be denied a ſmall fauour, which maketh entrance to a greater: then to be flatly refuſed altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a rygorous diſdayne, which ſhall continue him in diſgrace, and neuer
<pb facs="tcp:15023:35"/>more to be kindly lookt on. VVhereas if he had aduentured by little and little, the matter would not haue ſeemed ſo ſtrange vnto him, that at the firſt offer he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed poſſeſſion of full pleaſure: who ſo proceedeth otherwiſe, will finde it ſcantly to his owne pleaſing.</p>
            <p>I would aduiſe each man therefore to cenſure himſelfe, whether he be worthy to receiue ſuch familiarity or no, according to the time of his acquaintance with thoſe perſons: there is nothing more vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, then to be ouer-familiar at the firſt attempt, as ſeeking to reape before he haue ſowne; except he be ſo graciouſly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by the heauens, as to finde himſelfe ſo ſoone affected, as he doth affect: but the more certayne way is, to goe on by degrees ſtep after ſtep, as fearefull of thoſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences which may follow, and (aboue al) it is moſt expedient, to know our owne ſelues, without priuat flatterie; &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our imperfections, to amende, or wiſely conceale them, ſeruing our turne
<pb facs="tcp:15023:35"/>by more apt meanes: as to vſe good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, ſeeke benefit by ſtudy in the beſt letters: or if he follow armes, to winne this generall reputation that he is hardy, couragious, ready at all ſeaſons, making profit of that wherein he is expert, and not to meddle with any thing whereof he is ignorant; breefely, not to let the worldes eye note his ſecret deſectes.</p>
            <p>But if a man be ſlenderly fauoured by nature, let him vſe his minde ſo, as no one may regard but what is commendable in him; for a ſmall vice will be excuſed by a greater vertue: good grace may be thus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, either eloquence, vertue, knowledg, and whatſoeuer els is requiſite in a man. If the body ſecond not the minde; then he may ſay as a certayne great perſonage did, I am indifferently faſhyoned in minde: though I haue no comely forme of body, thus priuate giftes ſhould be reſpected before externall goods, for the graces of the minde are diſcerned in ſuch, as haue got more aduantage by their laudable qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:36"/>then they that deme themſelues for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate by beautie. And true it is, that ſuch men ought firſt to expreſſe the goodnes of their mindes, before they ſhould lay hold on loues familiarities: for when it ſhall be knowne what he is, to wit, a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, honeſt and gentle perſon, he will be accepted for his vertues and deſertes.</p>
            <p>It behoues him likewiſe to haue a good report: for diuers times we haue hard and ſeene, that ſome haue fallen in loue, euen by the good renowne of the parties. To ſet downe here precept vpon precept, as all thoſe things which are required in a courtier, was neuer my intention, for then I ſhould neuer make an end: only I ſay, he ought to declare himſelfe, in the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and perfect manner that poſſible he can, he ſhould know all things, eſpecially thoſe that are moſt for the purpoſe, he ought boldly to ſpeake, confirming his ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings not by vulgar reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to vſe apt exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, compariſons well formed, meete woords, graue ſentences, tempering and managing
<pb facs="tcp:15023:36"/>all which good grace, be it in ſpeaking, or elſe in companying, ſuch action and geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is moſt beſeeming. But beyond all theſe, to haue an eſpecial care, if he expect profit by what he ſpeaketh, to chuſe tyme and place conuenient for it: for any thing looſeth much of his grace, when it is not deliuered in as apt a ſeaſon. Let not his ſpeeches be offenſiue to any, if he vſe woordes to vrge laughter, let it be doone modeſtly: that they conuert not eyther to tearmes of flatterie, or tauntes and nippes which may ſtir the life blood: for the reſt, I refer him to <hi>Baltazar,</hi> who in the paſſage of his courtier hath written moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly Yet to theſe before rehearſed, I could wiſh in him humilitie, for gentlenes, courteſie, and honeſty are the epithits of humilitie: that he ſhould make account of men, if he will haue men make account of him: not to interrupt or breake of mens co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to yeeld a reaſon: for his ſayings, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>outſtanding long vpon diſcourſe, or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the patience of his hearers: to carrie
<pb facs="tcp:15023:37"/>himſelfe likewiſe in ſuch ſorte, as ſtill to haue his eye on them in company, to ſee if what he ſayth be pleaſing or no, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be ſufficiently vnderſtood: to think and premediate before on his ſpeeches, becauſe many times one wearies his trends, by vttering conceptions not wel ordered, whereby he is conſtrayned to ſtop in the midway, and ſo with breaking of his tale, driues away his companie.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe neceſſarie, that his tearmes be vſuall and well known, not farre fetcht or vainely bumbaſted: drawne from woordes auncient, or coyned on ſuch new ſtampes, as very few or none do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them, which makes both them and the ſpeaker ridiculous. He ſhould not loſe himſelfe in his diſcourſe, or wander to by wayes, but ſhould leuell his ſpeeches to reſolued purpoſe and concluſion, where into it may haue a ſweete current and fall, yeelding the whole courſe queint, eaſie, and intelligible, leaſt the end be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before the, beginning. But this is more
<pb facs="tcp:15023:37"/>due to a matter of eloquence, and becauſe there are great perſonages, who haue ſet downe certayne rules and enſtructions thereto belonging: I would counſell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ioy in the labours of them that haue ſo well deſerued of vs, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch good courſes for our better di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>I reckon eloquence, and a well ordered kinde of ſpeaking, to be neſſeſſarie for a Courtier, as a man who hath ſome need of perſwaſion, and ſpeech is miſtreſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in men, beeing the thing that onely forceth and prouoketh men on: As for geſture and countenaunce, it is very hard (in this meane treatiſe) to ſpecifie what a Courtier therein is to know: onely this I would aduertiſe him, that there are two things which may much auayle him; the firſt is to take example by them that doe well, and are of beſt enſtruction; the other, is to remember the defectes of ſuch as are vicious, and euermore to be warned by their bad courſes. For if the firſt meane of
<pb facs="tcp:15023:38"/>immitation be not ſufficient, there is no man whatſoeuer, who ſees a man of leaud demeanour, and worſſe lookes; but preſently will thinke ſcorne to immitate him, or reſemble him in any condition: to ſheeld himſelfe from deriſion, and poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at as a weake wit, vnfurniſhed, and worthie to be excluded all good compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Becauſe, when one ſees a man commit a groſſe fault, he ſhould receiue this as a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for himſelfe: for we can more eaſily diſcerne blemiſhes in others, then good qualities in our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Let him then make his profit of all, and endeauour to follow the perfection he ſhall gather by all: of ſome, modeſt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete ſpeech, of others, ciuill &amp; commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable behauiour, and ſo the reſt as their vertues merit immitation, according as it is ſayde the paynter <hi>Zeuxis</hi> did, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his <hi>Venus</hi> by the perfections of diuers choyſe maydens. He muſt chaſtiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by others blemiſhes, and till he bee aſſured of very good footing, not to preſſe
<pb facs="tcp:15023:38"/>in publique, but attend the houre of better abilitie.</p>
            <p>To talke of great matters, with waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie woordes, letting light occaſions paſſe like themſelues, not dwelling on any, except it be a matter ſerious and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: for els he will be noted that in ſmall trifles, he makes a very mightie loſſe of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe he who would ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe among others, ought not to be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all thinges, which may ordinarily hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in diſcourſe: he ſhould be very ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in hiſtories, but eſpecially in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophie, out of which (as from the fountayne) is deriued the ground of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and no man ought relye ſo much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his owne naturall iudgement, as the boundleſſe riches of others labours, whence he may learne experience in all thinges; as examples for gouernment of a common wealth, for warre, deuiſions, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lees, and other matters concerning the weale publique.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:39"/>
            <p>And although it may be thought ſtrange, that diſcourſing here of loue, I ſpeake of things which appertayne not ſo much to women, as to men: neuertheleſſe it is moſt certayne, that they who meddle with loue ſhall moſt part of their time meete with graue &amp; diſcreet me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea, in the preſence of their miſtreſſes, where they haue fit occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſtirre themſelues, by deliuering their knowledge in pollitique affayres, learning and other commendable quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: beſides it is more auayleable to reporte them in the preſence of their louers, then whatſoeuer they can ſay all their life time after to them, concerning loue. For a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man (to whom learning, and knowledge in moſt important affayres are not vſuall and familar) reuerenceth and makes great reckoning of them indued therewith: as one very well ſayth, ignoraunce begetteth admiration, and we grow amorous of ſuch thinges as we haue not, becauſe the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them is ſtraunge and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. While then the man hath this aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb facs="tcp:15023:39"/>ouer a woman, he may well ſerue his owne turne if he be wiſe, and yet without preſumption or affection. For preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a ſigne of a mans pleaſing himſelfe, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing glorie to his owne actions, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and condemning the deedes of others, becauſe himſelfe would be exalted aboue them. Preſumpion is very daungerous, in language, behauiour or otherwiſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is euermore to be ſhunned, as much becauſe it diſpleaſeth, as alſo in regarde it hinders credit of whatſoeuer we ſaye, for each one would keepe himſelfe from an hydden enemie: moreouer I haue heard, that the arte reputed to be moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, is it which maketh leaſt ſhewe of arte, but conceales it ſelfe with greateſt diſcretion.</p>
            <p>I would prohibite an other kinde of preſumpion, which is, when one diſcouers himſelfe ouer curious in ſpeaking: rather couet to be plaine &amp; honeſt in tearmes, ſuch as beſt become nature and true education. Hereto I adde a man in ſuch ſorte muſt
<pb facs="tcp:15023:40"/>reſpect his buſineſſe, as he make not his loue knowne, before he be acquainted with the diſpoſition of the perſon, to whom he hath deuoted his affection: for it is the cuſtome of women, to diſire what they leaſt ſeeme willing of, and deſpiſe thoſe things they are poſſeſſed of, therfore fore if a man would encreaſe their deſire, he muſt not come to publique gaze, but ſeeke occaſion of priuate acquaintaunce, as not making expreſſe intent to her, or her goods: neyther would I haue him to ſhew too much ſemblaunce of regarding her loue, becauſe ſome are of ſuch an humour, to flye when they are followed, and yeeld when they are leaſt ſought vnto. I knowe well there are ſome of ſo good ſorte, as the onely meanes of obtayning them, is to let them vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a mans paine &amp; dilligence imployed for their kindnes, and that loue is like the Adamant, which drawes the y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron to it, begetting affection in the partie beloued. But I leaue to mens diſcretions ſuch kinde of managing their affayres, and
<pb facs="tcp:15023:40"/>as they ſhall perceiue the mindes of their miſtreſſes to be ordered.</p>
            <p>If they be ſo happie, as to haue well cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and euidently diſcerne themſelues in grace, let them be the wiſer in keeping and preſeruing this fortunate fauour, by ciuill demeanour, and vertuous carriage: for he preuailes very much, that makes himſelfe treaſurer &amp; ſecretarie of his ladies neareſt thoughts, whereto reaſon is his beſt guide, which directs him in effectuall diſcloſing his loue to her, at ſuch tymes as beſt yeeldes him opportunitie without euer falſifying his loyaltie or breach of any gentle action.</p>
            <p>VVho ſo obſerueth theſe courſes, ſhall find much more contentment, then others doe torments in their vayne and vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſſions, but if his quiet be not ſuch as he could deſire, let him ſmoother all with ſilence, and comfort himſelfe by this verſſe of the Poet.</p>
            <q>To louers, hard fortune is euermore a common Stepmother.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:41"/>
            <p>See now breefely what I haue handled in this diſcourſe, concerning the principall meanes of winning grace with perſons of honour: It now remaynes to ſpeake ſomewhat of that which followeth, where ſuccinctly is handled the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of Loue.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:41"/>
            <head>The conſiderations of Loue. The fourth diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>IN mine oppinion, he that loueth, ought to conſider, to what end he loueth, the qualitie of her he loueth, and alſo the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to compaſſe his intent: leaſt he chaunce to finde his hopes fruſtrated, as many doe that loſe their time, and make themſelues ridiculous to the worlde. And for his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enſtruction herein he muſt know, that there is both a generalitie and a perticula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, in our behauiour towarde women.</p>
            <p>As for the generalitie; it is vſuall to all ſuch as make profeſſion of skill in cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: that we ſhould be gratious to all, and ſhew our ſelues ſuch as we would be eſteemed. Which vrgeth a fayre miſtreſſe to particularize her conceite, to ſhew ſuch regard as is not common or vulgare, and enricheth her with the attendance of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:42"/>as alſo cauſeth the like in men by their miſtreſſes. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one addictes not himſelfe to one certayne place, but remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ignorant what may betide him: he can neyther conclude on this or that, but makes a generall carriage of himſelfe, not yeelding or denying any one, becauſe he is vncertayne who ſhall be his loue. In like manner, a mayden not as yet ſtayed in her affection, being in companie, ſhewes her ſelfe gentle and affable to al ingeneral, not reiecting any one, but deliuering good lookes to all: becauſe it may ſo fall out, that one of them there preſent, whom yet ſhe leaſt dreameth on may one day be the man whom ſhe ſhall fancie.</p>
            <p>For an other reaſon, a man ſhould ſhew himſelfe generally gratious, as well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his minde therto, and ſo be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted honeſt, as alſo of euery one to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed courteous, whereby he may draw the affection to him of all ingenerall: that ſo beeing pleaſing to one and an other in particuler, the one abiding heere, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:15023:42"/>happily further off, yet ſtill good conceite of him meeteth together, and ſuch vertuous reporte is ſpred abroade of him, as from man to man his renowne is eſpecially regarded.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, he is not to abuſe himſelfe, though he haue the good reſpect and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of others: for honeſt men are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by their actions, as a graue man ſaid; that the ſun diſdained not to caſt his eie on things ſcant faire &amp; that which contenteth the eie, is indifferent to all the body beſide.</p>
            <p>Heer to I muſt ioyne, that he who would haue honor, doth feare the diſliking of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſons, and willingly would not bee diſpleaſing to any one, to auoyd procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the meaneſt enemie: for him whom we leaſt account of, may perhaps do vs greateſt iniurie, if he ſhal report vs to be proud and deſertleſſe. Therfore beware of offending any man, rather let vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane our ſelues, that cach one may gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally affirme thoſe things of vs, which we would deſire ſhould be beſt diſcerned in vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:43"/>
            <p>Nor would I haue a man ſo amorous of himſelfe, that when he hath but once ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to a woman: becauſe ſhe ſhe wes no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther behauiour but her vſuall kinde of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination: preſently he perſwades him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the man muſt haue her, and ſo growes forgetfull of his owne dutie. And this which I ſpeake to men, may be as well applyed to women, that they ſhould not lightly beleeue the ſmootheſt tongues, but conſider, there needeth a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger courſe of time, wherby to get acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his hart and intenhtion, and a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great conſequence, is not obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the firſt attempt: therefore they ought to be diſcreete and iudge with the time, which is an excellent meane to know one man from an other, who is too much knowen before. And I would haue them to obſerue a mediocritie in their profes, to wit, that as at the firſt motion they ſhould not yeelde, yet not to reiect or caſt men off ſo cruelly, as I know ſome haue done, who ſo ſoone as they are ſpoken too, will
<pb facs="tcp:15023:43"/>not abide to heare a woord of loue, but are ſo ouer-haſtie in returning an anſwere, that immediately they breake into theſe tearmes: They are not as they take them for, nor ſhould they offer them any ſuch ſpeeches, neyther ſhould a ciuill mayden know any ſuch matters. But men are ſo apt in diſcouering their owne follies, and readie to intrapt euerye well meaning mayde, hauing their mouthes full of loue and their harts quite emptie: theſe &amp; ſuch like are their nice wanton anſwers. Then muſt a man needs take it very ſtraungly, to be refuſed before he haue any thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded or ſpoken of ſuch matters as they impute vnto him: which apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declareth, that they long time exerciſed themſelues what anſweres to make, as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to al purpoſes, either right or wrong, without diſcretion or difference of ſuch as ſpeake to them, neyther declaring any other pacience, but that a fit way is layd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, to make them diſcouer that they knowe ſomewhat: whereas if they were
<pb facs="tcp:15023:44"/>better aduiſed, they would ſhape their anſwers perticularly to the queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, without any iournall courſe of replying, which ſeemeth no other then as a common ſong.</p>
            <p>VVhoſoeuer therefore will be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of good minde, and know withall what it is to anſwere: ought firſt to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande the party that ſpeaketh, euen as if he were an ambaſſadour, vntil he come to his ſpeeches concluſion, except he grow forgetfull of his owne dutie: then may ſhe well reproue, reprehend or by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him to knowe, that ſhe is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the valliditie of ſuch affayres, yet this care likewiſe muſt be had, the anſwere muſt not be common or vulgar, as long ſtudied before for windie phraſes and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy circumſtances: but in euery part to contayne ſuch diſcretion, that neyther in the matter or language affection be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe ſome that are not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the latine, think it the beſt courſe to talke curiouſly and finnically, flaying
<pb facs="tcp:15023:44"/>or ſtripping the latine tongue of choyſe and truct woordes, being ſo ouer daintie in their ſpeaking, as no one vnderſtandeth what they ſay, nor yet themſelues neither. It is beſt therefore to ſpeake what we know, not that we are ignorant of, neyther ſhould we wade further into any matter, then we may get out with credit and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſie.</p>
            <p>As concerning men, I find fault with ſome, who know not how to entertayne a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle woman, but onely in telling her; that they are ſo exceeding amorous, as they muſt needes dye: which often tymes is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with ſo ill a grace, as they are rather ſcorned then any way pittied. Others there bee that are ſo ſhameleſſe, as forgetting all courſe of modeſtie, vrge their ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citings to honeſt married wiues, who reckon nothing dearer then their honor and reputation: but ſuch ill nurtred gromes, doe I turne ouer to a certayne Ladies anſwere, which ſhe made to
<pb facs="tcp:15023:45"/>one who in the like manner moued her, which was as followeth. VVhen I was a childe (quoth ſhe) I learned obedience to my parents, &amp; dayly performed it: ſince I became a maried wife, I was taught the like leſſon towardes my huſband. If then the demaund you make to me be iuſt and honeſt, goe firſt and acquaint my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band therewith: and if he like of it, then ſhall you quickly haue my opinion after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; who can deny, but that this was an anſwere beſeeming a modeſt and vertuous woman?</p>
            <p>There are other, who will vſe the like ſpeeches to a woman, as they doe to an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney or a merchant, &amp; talke with a young mayden, as if they ſpake vnto her Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother: cheefely at weddings, or (which is worſſe) in maskes &amp; ſuch like, demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues ſo ſillily, that they open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are noted to be ridiculus, and to couer their faces to no other ende, but leaſt their ſhamefull bluſhing ſhould be apparantly diſcerned. Then are their orations ſo bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:15023:45"/>ordered, as they well deſerue baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, out of all good companie, and to goe worke out their apprentiſhippe in other places more meete for them. This ought to be obſcrued as well in men as women, not beeing bound to any one, but rather as readie for one as another: wherein they ſhould ſo wiſely gouerne their beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, that loue may be more beneficiall then hurtfull to them. But now I come to ſpeake of him, who perticulerly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth one woman onely, to whom his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and vowes are ſelemnely addicted</p>
            <p>If his loue be to marrie her, he knowes well by what degrees he muſt proceed, he ought firſt to conſider both his owne qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and hers, then to gayne her good conceite in ſuch ſorte, as nothing may come to her eare of him, but what may be pleaſing, as beeing a man generally belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and eſteemed: for a mayde will neuer let her honor depend on ſuch a man, as in company ſhal be a ſhame both to himſelfe &amp; her, nor will ſhe elect ſuch a one for her
<pb facs="tcp:15023:46"/>guide and heade, whom ſhe may imagine of weaker carriage then her ſelfe, for hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly can ſhe vſe obedience to him, that hath no ſufficiencie in aduiſing her, nor man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode to commaund, as indeede he ought to do. Let a man therefore conſider, what good partes he hath in himſelfe, which ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may make him regarded, or contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſpiſed: els, let it be no greefe to him, if he paſſe by as not noted and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected.</p>
            <p>In like caſe, a mayden ſhould ſhew her ſelf ſuch toward a man, as ſhe would deſire to be eſteemed, loued and ſought after. I will not, neyther can I ſet downe all the rules and precepts, that he or ſhe ought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, who will be pleaſing and agreeable one to the other; by reaſon they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and may more eaſily, be learned of them they keepe companie withal, by noting in each one, what is good or euill.</p>
            <p>It remaineth now to ſay ſomwhat of him, that loues a woman without reſpect of
<pb facs="tcp:15023:46"/>mariage, he muſt well know the humor &amp; complexion of her, whether ſhe be of that kinde that loues to giue the horne, comon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called a ſhort heeld friend, who are ſo ingenious, as they raiſe a ſlame in the heads of their followers, before they come ſcarſly to touch their fingers. Such can wel skil of diſpencing with affection, making in ſnew neuertheles, that they would be ſought to: but being once entertained into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, they are familiar with euery one, make no ſpare of their kindneſſe, eſpecially where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny commoditie is to be gotten, requiting them with nothing elſe, but the ſmoke of hope. Of theſe there are too many, &amp; they are ſoone heard of by the rumor that goes of them: with them it is dangerous to coh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, but euen to learne faſhions and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne their behaniour, ſing them as we do a knife againſt a grind ſtone, for no better benefit is to be made of them.</p>
            <p>But for him who in theſe affaires would begin his apprentiſhip, him would I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe to follow farre better courſes, and employ his leyſures to more auayling.
<pb facs="tcp:15023:47"/>True it is, that if he could ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund himſelfe, as to feigne the burden, without bearing it, diſſembling to loue, and yet feele no paſſion: he might enioy all the pleaſures in the world, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the cunning of ſuch miſtreſſes, whom he ſhould quickly beguile by counter: maſquing with them.</p>
            <p>For, were it not that a man applies him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the beſt enſtructions, and torments himſelfe more then is required: he could not but haue pleaſure in his loue, making vſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities which other gayne thereby. But when in good playe, good monye is ſtakte downe, eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is forborne, and the nyghts ſpent in building Caſtles in the ayre, all day wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſollitarie, one while dreaming on one imagination, then another, now rayling agaynſt his life, then curſſing his miſfortune, and all theſe complaintes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed priuately to himſelfe: then hath he neede to learne true ſufferance indeed, for then (the wiſeſt man in the world ſo afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
<pb facs="tcp:15023:47"/>ſhall finde he hath worke inough to to buſie himſelfe withall.</p>
            <p>Now as for our fine wanton, that will quickly be courted, ſhe maketh it her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to deceiue her followers, and hath no other delight, then when by a man (cold in affection) ſhe perceiueth now ſhe muſt beſtirre her wittes, and labouring with her deuiſes, ſhe ſomewhat enkindles him, and finding him growen a little more tractable, ſhe beginnes to lift him vp with the windy promiſes of hope, that afterward when he falles, he may be bruſed for euer. This is her paſtime, euen as the hunter ſporteth himſelfe in the chaſe, or as the cat, that playes ſo long with the mouſe ſhe hath taken, vntill at length ſhe deuoures it altogeather.</p>
            <p>Suth kinde of women take delight to be beloued, onely to haue amorous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes readie at all ſeaſons, as hating to be deſtitute of companie, albeit they ſcorne and flout them to their faces, foading them off with delay and dalliance. Sometime
<pb facs="tcp:15023:48"/>they let them come within two fingers breadth of the place deſyred, and then ſtart away, as it were manie a myle off. One while they giue good lookes, then with winckes and noddes appeare highly diſpleaſed, and all this is but to make their appetite the more vehement.</p>
            <p>There be other, who haue ſeruaunts of diuers ſortes, ſome that they ſport withall in ſecret, others that muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with expences, and theſe do ſerue but as ſhaddowes to the former, who being neuer ſo little miſuſed by them, will pretend great diſpleaſure, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing the other, to be cauſers thereof, as hauing ſpoken to the defame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of their miſtreſſes, and iuſtifying them with oathes to be right honeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: then they muſt ſlep in betweene them, to allay this tempeſt, which the purſſe-foole well payes for: albeit he reape no other corne for his harueſt. The moſt parte of ſuch women are thus prouided of ſeruantes, for diuers
<pb facs="tcp:15023:48"/>diuers reſpectes and diuers vſes, knowing how to drawe monye from euery vayne, although they make no ſharpe inciſſion for it.</p>
            <p>This I ſpeake, becauſe ſuch as haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned them, haue firſt payde dearely for their acquaintance, as well witneſſeth that which is written of auncient Courtezanes, whoſe couetouſnes could not be ſuffiſed, with the great treaſures of puiſſant kings and monarches in former tymes: as of <hi>Demetrius</hi> to <hi>Lamia</hi> and <hi>Flora,</hi> who gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch infinite ſubſtance together as they made the Romane people heyres thereof. And that it is no otherwiſe, note but the foundation of thoſe proſtituting places, which onely came by couetouſneſſe: and if any fauour be had of ſome other out of that place, it will coſt ſo much the more, and the kindneſſe is the coſtlier, the more ſhewe of honeſtie it is ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed withall.</p>
            <p>VVith ſuch, a man muſt deale both wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cunningly, not louing any thing
<pb facs="tcp:15023:49"/>but what is to be ſolde, that is, the body, not to regard it as any good thing, but only to eſteeme her as a Courtezane, addicted to voluptuous pleaſure, without beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more coſt then needeth, or thinking to appropriate that to himſelfe, which is common and freely offered to all ingene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <p>Let their couetouſneſſe teache thee, that they are onely to be had for monye, howſoeuer ſubtilly they pretend to loue thee: ſo by diſcouering their falſhoode and trecherie, thou maiſt the better learne to deteſt their leaude liues.</p>
            <p>For they that make marchandize of their fleſh, and will ſell themſelues to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers whatſoeuer: it ſhall be good to ſhun their companie, except it be to beholde their impudencie, and ſo to growe in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred thereof, conſidering thus to himſelfe, while he is with her, that the embracings ſhe vſeth to him, is but for a peice of coine: as a waterman for his ſtipend carries ouer all commers, or as a Paraſite in a Comedy,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:49"/>who practiſeth to reſemble the partie he preſenteth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ouid</hi> hath giuen good ſtore of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, to ſuch as deale in the courſes of loue, to withdrawe themſelues with little dammage, as ſetting before their eyes the loſſe of their ſute, the great diſpleaſure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing diuers wayes, and many other ſuch like remedies in loue.</p>
            <p>There is another ſorte of miſtreſſes that are honeſt, and contract amitie with ſuch as are like themſelues, giuing al pleaſure &amp; contentment they can one to another, as in comforting, councelling, viſiting, ayding and ſuccouring: and this loue is but among the regarders of honor, meeting with ſuch as are of their owne inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. With them we ought diſcreetly to demeane our ſelues, without giuing occaſion to be ill thought or ſpoken of: For when ſuch payres of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection meete together, they muſt be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained according to their eſteeme &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, without offence offered on either ſide but in all pleaſing and perfect agreement.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:50"/>
            <head>Of Iealoſie. The fift diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>ALthough it be not ſo eaſyly diſcerned, what Iealoſie is to be blamed, and what to be excuſed, as it is eaſie to aſſure, that all Ileaoſie, in whatſoeuer perſon, or for what cauſe, is euermore an hinderaunce to the minde, and a very great torment: yet is it firſt to be iudged, whether Iealoſie be a vice or no, and to diſcide the the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the perſon and occaſion. For to condemne a man ſo ſoone as one ſayeth he is Iealous, is to be carried away by the common peoples oppinion onely, and blind-fold to follow a rumour in a Cittie, without hauing regard to the matter pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Then fgor our entraunce into this caſe, we will firſt define Iealoſie to be a grieſe, which a man hath by beeing depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of ſome good which he hath loued,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:50"/>and Iealoſie may be applyed to all thinges whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>God ſayeth, that he is Iealous, and will not haue the honour onely due to him, attributed to any other. The Gentleman ſayth, he is Iealous of his reputation: each one is Iealous of that he eſteemeth dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or is moſt carefull and charie of.</p>
            <p>If a husband haue ſuſpition of his wife, that her gouernment is not good or agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his liking, he is ſay de to be iealous, that is, he is diſpleaſed to ſee that wronged, which he thinketh onely belongeth to himſelfe. If a woman be offended, that her freend or mate keepes not loyaltie with her: ſhe likewiſe is reputed iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>Now to know whether Iealoſie in man or woman is vnſcemely, vicious and to be reiected, it is a matter, depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon circumſtances. And in trueth, it is a ſhame and imurie for a man to bee iealous, making him the leſſe eſteemed, as if the cauſe thereof thus proceeded, that this
<pb facs="tcp:15023:51"/>owne conſience makes him deeme him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnworthie of that he poſſeſſeth, or knowes his owne abilitie to be inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and ſo procureth a diſtruſt of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as imagining himſelfe not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, and that others (more deſeruing then he) are better affected, and eſteemed by his wife more then himſelfe is whereas if he were of deſert, an other could not go beyond him, nor carrie that away which onely appertayneth to him: in this ſorte, may iealoſie be counted a ſhame and great diſgrace to a man.</p>
            <p>But contrariwiſe, when I ſee them that winke at their wiues behauiour, and will take no knowledge that they are cornu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet are mockt and poynted at by others: I cannot chuſe but blame them for not beeing iealous, although not of their wiues, yet of their honour. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I can giue no better reſolution, then that which is vſed in all laudable actions, to wit mediocritie, which is an eſpeciall vertue of it ſelfe. And let me ſay withall, that as the
<pb facs="tcp:15023:51"/>vertue of liberally is betweene prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on the one ſide, and couetouſneſſe on the other, the one in wanting, the other in abounding, and as the vertue of ſtrength, is betweene timeritie and puſillanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: euen ſo the diſcretion which ought to be in a married man, ſhould be betweene iealoſie on the one ſide, and negligence or no regard on the other. For, to be ſo ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie in his buſineſſe, as (not to ſee at all) that which all the world diſcerneth, is both beaſtlineſſe and inconſideration: likewiſe, to take offence, and cauſeleſſe to carrie ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition tin minde, declares the want of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and diſcretion.</p>
            <p>There is no man of ſo baſe and abiect ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that will ſuffer one to reproch him, with his wiues giuing him the hornes, for ſuch monſters are infamous bothy by fact and right, euen as a knowen and publique noted baude: ſo that were it but in this reſpect, the lawe reputes ſuch as deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if they ſhall compound and make ſale of their wiues addulteries. Here hence it
<pb facs="tcp:15023:52"/>proceedeth, and by right is permitted as a matter excuſable, for a man to kill his wife, beeing found in ſuch an offence, which prerogatiue is no way tollerated in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. The reaſon why the fact is more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated in the woman then the man; is, becauſe adulterie in a woman, makes doubt of her iſſue, whether it be by her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or an other, which cannot carrie like miſtruſt in a man. Ye ſhall haue ſome that alledge an other reaſon, which notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I will not defend, and I am certayne, that all they who haue any feeling of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wil herein iump with mine oppinion. For they ſay, that the man beeing the head of his wife, as much to ſay, as Lord ouer her, ſhe ſtandeth the more obliged in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of her fayth and loyalty: If then ſhe fall to violate that ſtrict bond, ſo much the more ſhame and damagement dooth the man ſuſtayne in his goodes. The firſt part of their reaſon is not to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, neyther indeede doe I ſo raſhly cenſure of it: but in regarde of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion
<pb facs="tcp:15023:52"/>cluſion they make thereof, I ſay they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume a little ouermuch, and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be very abſurd, euen (as it were) in auouching playne paganiſme. For if they will conclude, that becauſe it is ſo, that a man is the head and Lord of the woman, therefore ſhe hath no power at all ouer him, and ſo conſequently it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for him, without any contradiction to abandon her and giue himſelfe to all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous pleaſures: I ſay ſuch as are of this oppinion differ not at a I from the paganes, who indeede doe mayntayne, that when a lewd quailitied man, ſubiect to his owne deſires, ſhul offend with ſome freend of his, or eis his chamber mayd; neuertheleſſe his wiſe muſt not be diſpleaſed there with, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way reproue him for it: but rather ſhe ſhould eſteeme the better of him, and that this was done in reuerend reſpect of her, as not ſuffering lier to pertake in his drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, beaſt-like luxurie, and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce at that tyme.</p>
            <p>Perhaps herein they would immitate the kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who when they
<pb facs="tcp:15023:53"/>feaſted and banquetted in ordinarie and comely manner, they would then haue their wiues ſit with them at the table. But when they carrowſed and dranke till they were drunke, their wiues were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to their chambers, and then their concubines, women ſingers and dauncers muſt be with them.</p>
            <p>Now diuers (at the firſt iudging hereof) deemed they did well, in that they would not haue their lawfull wiues, participate with their drunken diſſolution: but then they might as eaſily herein haue conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red withall, that vnder this pretext of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to their wiues, they permitted themſelues to runne into all corruption and infamy of their liues; for among ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people, neuer will a modeſt wife ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her huſband, to entertayne a ſtrumpet neare her, as well for auoyding diſcorde, as preuention of iealoſie, whereunto women are naturally ſubiect.</p>
            <p>But admit that ſuch accidentes ſhould befall them, and their huſbandes are ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted
<pb facs="tcp:15023:53"/>to affect ſtrumpets: yet is it great iniuſtice done them, that for a little vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous diſorder, they will ſo much wrong, diſpleaſe and iniurie their wiues, and not doo at leaſt like the poore ſillie Bees, who in no caſe will themſelues touch rudely their proper females, but if any other of their company wrong them, they will warre with them rather then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Notwithſtanding all this, there are found too too manie, ſo bad of minde and diſpoſition, as will not ſticke to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie their owne wiues, comming defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and poiluted from the baſe aſſociation of ſome others: and then behaue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſuch ſort with them, as if all the world were not able to reproue them: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remembring how commonly it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, that the faults whichment commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wiues, are more rumoured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people, then thoſe of their wiues toward them. As we may ordinarily note in him, that keepes no good gouernement in his houſe and familie: If he be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:15023:54"/>by his wife, one of theſe too occaſions are immediatly vrged, either that he is blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his owne behauiour, and hath no eyes at all to diſcerne matters happening: or elſe himſelfe is conſenting to the ſhame, and hath no vertue lefte in him to gaineſay it, but, as one ouermaiſtred by his wife, too baſely ſubiects him ſelfe, and ſo is led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by the noſe, as one doth a beaſte.</p>
            <p>There are none more infamous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, then ſuch wreched kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who deſerue to be publiquely nayled to poſtes, and of their infamie can neuer be ſpoken ſufficient: ſuch a one may be called <hi>Iohn Iohn,</hi> that goes for wine while his wife tends her paſtime, and if any harme be doone, he lookes through his fingers, for feare he ſhould ſee it, or (like a kinde foole) ſits and watcheth the doore.</p>
            <p>Contrary wiſe, when a man is Iealous without a cauſe, looking with a cloudie countenance, ſuſpitiouſly diſcontented, it is a verie great blemiſh to him: he ſtirres
<pb facs="tcp:15023:54"/>others therby to more forwardnes in his buſines, then reaſon accounteth expedient, and happily may ſo come by ſome cauſe for his iealoſie, he prouokes his wife to waxe careleſſe of him, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For there is no readier way to bring a woman to looſenes of life, then in ſuffering her to ſee his apparant ſuſpition, that he reputes her as a woman diſhoneſt, grues her hard vſage, watcheth wherſoeuer ſhe walkes, wherby ſhe perceiuing, that her huſband repoſeth no credit in her loyaltie, ſhe preſently takes her ſelfe as little obliged to him, by reaſon the league of communitie in faith betweene them, is broken by diſtruſt on his behalfe: then ſhe ſtandes vppon her better deſeruing, that he is no meete man for her, ſhe too good a wife for him, and ſo neglects all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty toward him.</p>
            <p>I could, as fitting this purpoſe, produce ſufficient teſtimonie, of ſuch as haue beene extreamely iealous, ſome procuring
<pb facs="tcp:15023:55"/>their wiues (through their owne bad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour to ward them) to commence ſute in law againſt them, whereby ſuch ſhame hath redounded to the men, that the wiues haue beene found of able ſufficiencie, and their hushands to be impotent, faultie, and ouermuch to blame, whereby hath eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeared, that their own weakneſſe and diſhabilitie was cauſe of their iealoſie.</p>
            <p>What comfort or contentment can a poore woman haue, to be accompanyed with ſuch a beaſt, as is euery houre wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching her, holdes his wife as a priſoner, cannot endure ſhee ſhould ſpeake to anie one, becauſe he reputes her fraile and eaſie to fall? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe but liſt to a queſtion demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhe is preſently loſt, and the deed hath beene dooen, though ſhe ſtird not out of his companie. Heerein therefore, there muſt be vſed more wiſdome and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they that will auoide theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked extremities, muſt obſerue thoſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that are vertuous and commendable.</p>
            <p>One thing moſt requiſite betweene
<pb facs="tcp:15023:55"/>them which are loouers, is to carie a good conceit of her he affecteth, to repoſe ſuch truſt in her, as neuer to gaze after her, but let her goe on her owne conſciences direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. heervpon enſueth, that ſhe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his vndo inted truſt, and how his oppinion is conſident in her: ſhe will not doo any thing vnwoorthie of his looue, or ſeeme ſo much as in thought to deceiue him, but yeeld him like vertuous &amp; mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all affection In li'e manner, if a huſband manifeſt to his wife, that his truſt is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely repoſed in her, diſcouerſe his ſecrets to her, &amp; perfectly declareth, that he reputs her fora right good woman: he doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke his wife, to be moſt loy all and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him, and makes her thus conceiue within her ſoule, that it were moſt ſhame full to deceiue him, who is ſo firme in his oppinion of her.</p>
            <p>The law imputes it as an infamie, to him that makes deniall of a gadge, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect it is held as a courteſie to a freend, in whom good conceite &amp; truſt is repoſed,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:56"/>and one ſayth, that it is a moſt villainous thing, to deceiue the fayth of another, beeing holy and inuiolable; by much more reaſon then, if a man bee Iealous and ſuſpicious without cauſe, dooth he wrong and iniurie to his yoke mate, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming her otherwiſe then anhoneſt good woman. If once he grow to that imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe well perceiues that he loues her not: which makes her breake all fayth and amitie, taking iuſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be at deadly defiaunce with him, hating him as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie which hath highly abuſed her, and ſo practiſeth reuenge on the wronger of her reputation: for ſhe hath nothing dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then her honour, without which, ſhe dares not ſhew her face to any.</p>
            <p>A man muſt likewiſe conſider, that a woman is not of ſuch a ſeruill condition, as to be gouerned by feare, for when one thinkes to bridle her, then will ſhe ſooneſt ſhake it off, and the more ſhe is conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the more ſhe reſiſteth and ſtandeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:56"/>
            <p>He therefore that will ſhun falling into theſe inconueniences ought with reaſon, (which is the onely bridle, whereby to guide a diſcreet man or woman) to check ſuch bad conceites in himſelfe, and doe nothing compulſiuely: for the minde beeing inuiſible, and not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſence, obeyes to nothing but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſhe is the ſole gouerneſſe of al our actions: that if he be a man who ſwerues from reaſon, yet let him not be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him that ſinneth, and will neuer yeeld ſome reaſon for the cauſe of his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, at leaſt ſome outward ſeeming ſhewe of reaſon.</p>
            <p>VVho-ſo-euer will be beloued, ought himſelfe to loue; who ſeekes to haue truſt repoſed in him, ought yeeeld like confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to another; who would receiue good, ought to doe good: for we muſt expect the ſame meaſure from others, which we our ſelues haue extended to them.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, when I ſay a man
<pb facs="tcp:15023:57"/>ſhould be ſaythfully reſolued of his wife, my meaning is, ſhe giues him no bad occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to deeme otherwiſe then wel of her, be couſe ſuch reſpects doe euermore deliuer beſt conceites of her: for we repute a man to be wiſe, when his behauiour is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to according ſpeaking diſcreeteſy, caryng himſelſe wiſely, and farre from the touch of any ſcandale. We likewiſe iudge a man to be lewd when we perceiue his manners to be diſſolute, imſpriſing all ouncel to ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill demeanour, &amp; bearing himſelfe in ſuch ſorte, that he is hated and ſhund of all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people. huen ſo a woman ſhall be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly cenſured of, if her habit bee like theirs that is vertuous and honeſt, if ſhe frequent the companie of women well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of, and vſe no language but what is honorable: where contrariwiſe, if ſhe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low reprochfull companie, perſons that are defamed, go diſſolutely in her attire, ſpeake lightly, without regard of ſhame and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, ſhe ſhal be thought a ſtragler, proud, a pratler, bolde and impudent.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:57"/>
            <p>Now to know for certaintie, whether ſhe is not to be taxed with the crime of diſhoniſtie or no, little can be ſayd therein, by reaſon the act is ſo ſecret: but ſuch as haue bad reporte, and haue gruen occaſion to ſpeake ſiniſterly of them (albeit they may be verily innocent,) they ought to chaſtiſe their courſes and behauiour by good examples, that they may ſhunne all hard ſpeeches, both of themſelues and their huſbandes, ruminating continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene themſelues, this ſentence left by the wiſe man in writing: <hi>That good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowue is more worth, then a rich girdle of golde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Honour is nothing els but populare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, it is no parte of the conſcience: but he that feares not what men may ſaye of him, (as <hi>Caccro</hi> ſayeth) is wicked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſtable. On the other ſide, Sainte <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> telles vs, <hi>VVhoſoeuer giues a pardon to his owne conſcience, and neglects his good fame, is cruell to himſelfe and full of impietie,</hi> and this is it which we tearme to be ſcandalous. It
<pb facs="tcp:15023:58"/>is not enough then to haue innocencie in the hart, we muſt as well eſcape the giuing of occaſion, to men of euill reporte: of which occaſion I can ſpeak no otherwiſe, but euen as honor depends on the people, &amp; them that are wiſe: ſo if a man will haue honor, he muſt gouern him ſelf, as the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt &amp; beſt reputed among the people do, and not deſerue any other ſiniſter oppini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If then a woman doe demeane her ſelfe, in ſuch ſorte as hath beene declared, and yet her huſband (neuer-the-leſſe0 will be ſicke in the brayne, and fooliſh of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite: it remaynes to his owne perill, for ſhe is no iote diſhonoured thereby, but himſelfe, that without any cauſe became diſtruſtfull of her. Now let vs ſee whether Iealoſie be moſt dangerous in a man, or woman.</p>
            <p>Some holde, that the woman beeing weaker then the man, and leſſe able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte the aſſaultes, which iealoſie continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally afflictes the minde withall, ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the more ſubiect to paſſion: and in
<pb facs="tcp:15023:58"/>this caſe might a number of women be named, who beeing depriued of ſence and vnderſtanding, haue frantiquely and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly run about the ſtreetes. I can alledges no other reaſon in this behalfe, why in her it ſhould growe to ſuch an extremitie: but that a man feeles not like defect of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when his wife dooth ſtray in ſecrete, as a woman findes in her ſelfe, beeing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded of her due, as when her huſband partes with that to another, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and by right is none but hers. As for the woman, queſtionleſſe ſhe challengeth a mightie intereſt not ſo much in regarde of the pleaſure, as the breach of interchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged loue, ſeeing her ſelfe fruſtrated of the faith and kindeneſſe, which ſhe was wunt to find effectually manifeſted, and beſide, perceiuing her ſelfe halfe parted and ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from her moitie. Notwithſtanding all this, I finde that iealoſie is much more hurtfull in a man, then woman, becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; abous his perfect diſcouering, that the faith of mariage is violated (the ſelfe ſame conſideration being on the wifes behalfe) he
<pb facs="tcp:15023:59"/>feeles withall a ſhame and infamie, with ſuch ablemiſh and diſhonour, as is no way or at any tyme, repay reable agayne.</p>
            <p>And yet many princeſſes haue bene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to loue and reuerence their huſbandes exceedingly, albeit they haue had baſtardes by others, rather renewing then any way hindering their loue: but when honour once is wounded, it is a matter almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, for a man afterward to giue his wife good lookes, and not proue her as a bad creature, when once ſhe hath forfeited her fayth giuen to him.</p>
            <p>Many examples of vertuous dames are regiſtred in writings, that paciently haue endured this iniurie of their hufbands, nay more to ſee their concubines kept, euen in the very ſame houſe with them: the olde Teſtament, as alſo the hiſteries Greek and Romaine, want no ſtore of them, who haue enfranchiſed their ſeruauntes, that haue giuen entertaynment to their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes. But among men of generous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ye ſhall neuer finde any one, that
<pb facs="tcp:15023:59"/>would endure ſo much as a ſuſpition one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of their wiues: witneſſe <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> who did repudiate his wife, and when one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him the cauſe there of, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; becauſe he would hauchis wife voyde of ſuſpition, by much more reaſon then would he haue her free from detection of crime.</p>
            <p>Suſpition is that which brings diſhonor both to man and woman, therefore Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſie (of it ſelfe) is as yrkeſome to beare in a man as a woman, and ſo much the more in a man, becauſe thereby he looſeth his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>To tell what kinde of payne this iealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is, exceedeth poſſibilitie of expreſſing: for if the loſſe of goodes, of birth, of freends, or of parentes, be ſuch as torments and makes a man inmeaſurably paſſionate, how greeuous then will be the loſſe of his wife to him, of whom it is ſay de: <hi>Aman ſhall leaue ſather, mother, and all, and cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wife?</hi> If that bond and coniunction cannot be deaided or ſundred, but by death
<pb facs="tcp:15023:60"/>only: what ſhall become of him, who ſees him ſelfe diſioynd from amitie, and yet (for all that) ſtands tyed by his perſon? much better were if for him to looke vpon death, then continually to haue before his eyes the cauſe of his affliction, and ſee his enemie ſtill remaining aliue, reuiuing dayly the remembrance of the heinous wrong doone him.</p>
            <p>And euen as a man deemes him ſelfe happy, when he is conioyned in good and durable amitie with a wife, by whom he is entreated honorably, ſeruing as an ayde &amp; conſolation in his affayres: Euen ſo on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie, he reputes himſelf vnhappie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſted of wife, a deare frend and choyſe companion, he findes a deadly emmie, one that hath done him vnrecouerable ſhame, one that delightes in his death, and with whome hee hath no aſſurance of his life.</p>
            <p>Of like quality is this eſtate in a woman, when ſhe ſees her ſelfe forſaken and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. She that hath no honor, but by her
<pb facs="tcp:15023:60"/>huſband, finding her ſelfe to be contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; deſpiſed, to behold a baſe ſtrumpet preferred before her, to endure her braua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, inſteed of being ſupported by her lord and ſpouſe, to whom ſhe is vowed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, to whom ſhe hath giuen her goods and perſon, for whomſe choyſe ſhe iefuſed very many ſufficient offers, of whom ſhe might haue beene much better regarded and honoured: what life (I pray ye) is it to be thought that ſhe poore ſoule endureth? There is nothing that more offendeth any one, then to ſee himſelfe deſpiſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned: as alſo nothing more contenteth the hart, then to feele the loue and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of well willers, and iacloſie neuer commeth without conceie of ſcorne and diſdayne A woman ſeeing her ſelfe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed to a man, and giuing her ſelfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, no other are to bee regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by her: not finding the like in her huſbande, and honeſtly knowes not how to reuendge her wrong: what dooth ſhe then but weepe and lament?
<pb facs="tcp:15023:61"/>yet with all ſhe conſiders with her ſelfe, that the faultes in a man are corrigible, and tif ſhould he ſee the like blemiſh in ſome oher bad bodie, who therefore goes as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all men; it would be a meanes of his amendment.</p>
            <p>I haue ſeene diuers, who haue dearely loued their wiues, after they haue ſundry tvmes before gon away and forſaken them: but this doth hardly hold in ſome Linde of men, becauſe infamie remaynes in the woman, not in the man. God is more readie to pardon and forgiue a ſin, then man is, he forgets (withall) a ſinne ſo ſoone as he hath pardoned it, but a man dooth continually remember it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that honour is like to a glaſſe, which beeing once broken can neuer be made whole agayne.</p>
            <p>VVe haue ſpoken of iealoſie in man and wife, let vs ſaye ſomewhat of the ſame in amorous perſons, and to ſpeake truely, I finde, that loue (not being faſtened by by the ſcale of marriage) is dayly ſubiect
<pb facs="tcp:15023:61"/>to the changes of Fortune: for one while it hopes, a nother while deſpayres, now full of feare, then by and by aſſured, now doubting, then rioting, now in fauour, then reiected, often ending and beginning againe, according to the oppinion of <hi>Plato.</hi> It is an eſtate of no certaintie, and therfore from ſuch as are ſubiect thereto, iealoſie can very hardly be abſent: for delight is not tied therto, but if it be, it is with great danger and inconuenience.</p>
            <p>Therfore it is impoſſible, but iealoſie ſometimes muſt be medling therwith, yet not in ſuch daungerous ſort, as in the ſtate of mariage becauſe wher faith is not giuen, if any impeach happen, it is more excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then when faith feeles it ſelfe neglected and abuſed.</p>
            <p>Contrarywiſe, it ſeemes that iealoſie in looue is commendable, becauſe therby is witneſſed, how highly a man eſteemes her whom he affecteth, as beeing angry and diſpleaſed at vnkinde wordes, or gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for the abſence of his louer accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:15023:62"/>as one compares the caſe to a mother, that mournes for her infant, whome ſhee ſuppoſed loſt: which if ſhee ſhould not do, her affection might be ſaide to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſmall. For which, I would aduiſe ſome meane, as in all other things, for it enſues often times to great inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by brauadoes and repulſes giuen and taken: Therefore it becomes them, to deale wiſely and diſcreetely in theſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires,</p>
            <p>As concerning iealoſie betweene two friends, certainly it is to be reprooued, by reaſon diſtruſt engenders diſagreement, declaring the little credence and repute which eche holdes of other: for there is no man, but he will be offended at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie receiued by his friend, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his hope is fruſtrated, and he findes not his friend ſo entire, as he ſuppoed him to be.</p>
            <p>But in what amitie or friendſhip ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, icaloſie ought not to be, without ſome cauſe expreſſed and knowen.
<pb facs="tcp:15023:62"/>Likewiſe, it is verie hard to hinder it, when the occaſion is great, and too apparant. VVho loueth any thing dearely. feareth the loſſe thereof, and takes it more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly when it is loſt: The like eaſon of ſorrowing for ſuch loſſe, agrees with deep paſsion when it cannot be attained, but farre exceedeth, when it is quite loſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. For, to apart with a thing peaceably poſſeſt, is verie irkſome: whereas things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enioyed, cauſe the leſſe greeuance:</p>
            <p>It is not poſsible for a good mind, that loueth truely, and doth whatſoeuer he can for another: but he muſt needes be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, when he beholdes his loue not to be requited, but is anſwered with ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ingratitude, as if all his ſeed hath beene beſtowed vpon a barren ſoyle, and all his trauaile prooues fruitleſſe, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him no profite. But they who once are entred into a league of true amitie, ought on both ſydes verie care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerue their allianuce: for if at anye time it chaunce to bee bruiſed and
<pb facs="tcp:15023:63"/>broken, if it vnite agayn afterward, it is very wonderfull, except conſideration of that which cauſed the breache, doo prooue the meanes to help it againe: elſe it had beene much better for eyther part, that ſuch a vnion had neuer beene betweene them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:63"/>
            <head>Of the paſsions of Loue. The ſixt Diſcoure.</head>
            <p>LOue is a paſsion ſo forcible in our ſoules, as therein all affections are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned and compriſed. Foure things there are that do torment our mindes, and hat in ſuch ſort, as they ſeeme like the windes that toſſe a ſhip vp and downe: to wit, hatred, loue, feare, and hope. Theſe foure paſsions are in loue, and in ſuch order are they there, as they can neuer be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thence. The Poets in their writings, haue left vs ſufficient teſtemonie thereof, but muchmore is that which we feele and finde in our owne ſelues: Therefore, in regard of theſe foure affections, a man is hindered in iudgement, and ſo (by good right) is loue figured and ſet foorth to be blinde.
<pb facs="tcp:15023:64"/>Theſe foure, one after another in their ſeuerall degrees, doo occupie and labour the mindes of the amorous, and holdes them (as it were) in a continuall traualye: for when hope lifteth vp, feare and diſtruſt caſtes downe agayne: looue makes a man imagine it a pleaſure, but then ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde croſſe turnes is to greefe, and then he growes in hate of that which impeached him in his pleaſure. But aboue all, that which procureth moſte paine, is the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate looue we beare to our ſelues. which at the firſt fight may ſeeme very ſtraung: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that looues not, hateth him ſelfe, as one affirmeth, and there is nothing more contrarie to looue, then this <hi>Philaftia,</hi> which is nothing elſe but looue of our ſelues.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, becauſe I haue ſo found it by experience, I ſay, that he which looueth, and is not againe requited with the lyke, feeles nothing to him more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, then to ſee himſelfe miſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not liſtned to nor regarded: for then
<pb facs="tcp:15023:64"/>he growes to contempte of himſelfe, that he is not of any worth, hanſome or gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; but lothſome and vnfightly, when he beholdes an other preferd before him, and he repulſed at the very firſt onſet, then he laies all blame he can deuiſe on him ſelfe, alleadging theſe perſwaſions, that if he were of any deſert, or any matter woorth affecting were in him, his miſtreſſe would haue giuen him better entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or elſe (at the leaſt) would haue made ſome account of him.</p>
            <p>And ſo much the more, as nature hath giuen vs a care, to prochaſe to our ſelues all aduantages and benefits, to the end, that what ſhe hath brought foorth, might encreaſe, and be encreaſed in the firſt intir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: euen ſo is grefe the more hurtfull, when a man cannot reach to the degree of others affabilitie, and attayne thoſe good partes neceſſarie to make himſelfe affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo that a man holding nothing dearer, then emiche himſelfe with ſuch graces, as are generally beloued and deſired, feeles an
<pb facs="tcp:15023:65"/>exceeding diſlike, when he perceiues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe faultie, and ſome noted defect, makes him repulſed and not eſteemed.</p>
            <p>And it is very true, that we neuer know our owne imperfections, till we growe to deſire and aduancemente of our ſelues: for when we perceiue our croſſing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayning, then we doo finde more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of our ſelues.</p>
            <p>When a man keepes a piece of golde in his purſſe or cheſt, he knowes not then the eſtemation of it, he ſees it hath the couller, lookes very fayre, and hath the ſtampe impreſſed on it: but when he bringes it abroad, would deliuer it in payment, and ſees it brought to poyſing, to endure the touche or ſounding, and then it proues counterfeict by publique oppinion, why then he findes himſelfe nothing enriched by the piece, but a matter which is vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnaduantageable.</p>
            <p>The tryall of a man, is when he makes offer of him ſelfe, and ſtandes taxed to abyde good lyking or diſgrace.
<pb facs="tcp:15023:65"/>If then he be refuſed, firſt of all he findes fault with his want of deſert, becauſe (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) we naturally holde it as a ſingular commendation, to be perfect in all partes, and beeing deſirous of honour, we couet to be ſo eſteemed by others.</p>
            <p>It followes then that a man in this caſe nothing accounted of, greeues becauſe hee cannot compaſſe his inent, and ſees no other helpe, yet well vnderſtanding, that as he looues his miſtreſſe for a certayne oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, to wit, becauſe ſhe is fayre, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, gentle and honeſt: ſo ſhould he (on his parte) haue ſomewhat wherby to gaine her loue, for loue groundes his foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vppon ſome eſpeciall cauſe.</p>
            <p>Then when he ſees he hath nothing good in him-ſelfe, whereby to attract mooue, and procure her affection toward him: then he growes out of all hope of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his purpoſe, then he becomes ſad, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholique, ſolitarie, ſhunning the light and ſocietie of men.</p>
            <p>Neuer-the-leſſe, as we can very quickly
<pb facs="tcp:15023:66"/>make our ſelues beleeue, that there is ſome matter of worth remayning in vs, then hope yeeldes ſome mittigation: but comming then preſently agayne to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that we are not of any reckoning, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe the opinion of people is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and oftentymes a woman ſetteth her lyking on a man of leaſt deſcart: alas, it is impoſſible to conceiue, how much the poore minde is then tormented, with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall curſings &amp; exclaiming on the houre of our birth. But what would ſuch a man man doe, if he had a iudge there preſent to cenſure on his cauſe in loue? Doubtleſſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>would conceiue ſome hope, that the good, neſſe of his plea ſhould be to his aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and ſo to compaſſe that by iuſtice, which otherwiſe by fauour is vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him.</p>
            <p>But the eſtate of a man dependes on the inclynation of his miſtreſſe, ſhe is of this humour heere, then ſhe takes pleaſure annon to be there, and will not reſolutely determine on any thing, but ſtill is chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb facs="tcp:15023:66"/>in her oppinions.</p>
            <p>VVhat remedie can the poore man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to theſe moodes? he now intreates to proceede by her grace, and not in the iuſtice of his cauſe; his miſtreſſe is the iudge, and himſelfe ſtandes for his tryall: he beginnes his plea, but ſhe is become ſo humorous, as the more ſhe is followed, deſired and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated, the further of flyes ſhe, cloſing her eyes, cares and hart altogether, farre diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from them of beſt crudition, who hate to be touchte with any act of vngen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe.</p>
            <p>There are two wayes to winne a woman by, to wit, delectation, which makes her beautie eſteemed, and ſo to be deſirous of iouiſſaunce: of which kinde there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which ſeeme colde enough outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, eyther by courſe of nature in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or deeming that they are fayre enough for them. The other is, when they are deſirous of the beautie of the minde for then they make reconing of any good doone them, or of ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:15023:67"/>enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes them with ciuill demeanour. But the miſchiefe is, that the moſt parte are ſo curious of their bodies, beſtowing ſo much tyme time in decking themſelues like pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets: that they neuer thinke at all on the dignitie of the minde, and when they are with ſuch, as would giue them ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment in their thoughts, eyther becauſe they are not capable of any good thing, or not willing to be therewith acquainted; they turne their heades aſyde, contenting themſelues with their delicate decking, to ſhew a good countenaunce, vſe many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as alſo to be generally gazed on and purſued by many, that if now and then they vouchſafe ſo much fauour, as to liſten the ſpeeches of an honeſt gentle minde, they doe it but to be lookt at by others, and to carrie the reporte, that they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued and ſoughtafter, not minding at all what els is then ſayde to them.</p>
            <p>But as forthem that are agreeable to their diſpoſition, entertayning them with ſportes and recreations: it falles out often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes,
<pb facs="tcp:15023:67"/>that they are the verieſt ſottes, and moſt vnfurniſhed by nature, but in reſpect they be braue and gallant, they are the beſt welcome, and cheefeſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured.</p>
            <p>Nor let vs meruayle ouer-much heereat, becauſe like muſt ſtill agree with like, and the one ſhould not mocke the other: therefore he that yeeldes them any courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, eſpecially in publique, he muſt be very braue, for the goodlier man hee is, and coſtlier apparelled, the more do they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine them-ſelues to be honoured, when they are followed and fauoured of any ſuch.</p>
            <p>Now they that carry another reſpect, then to be Lackyed by hueries, or helde with friuolou diſcourſings, or in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus to declare any other behauiour, then may beſeeme their modeſtie and diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: it is hell to them to be otherwiſe ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for if they deſire entertaynemeut by any, they muſt then be ſuch as themſelues are, reſpectiue of a maidens good fame and
<pb facs="tcp:15023:68"/>reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for when any other language is vſed to them, then agrees with their liking and vnderſtanding, they quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye finde meanes to leaue ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie.</p>
            <p>But if we come a little nearer, to conſider the behauiour of theſe nice ones, &amp; what pickt ceremonies they vſe in their cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, we ſhall beholde the onely follies in the worlde: one will ſtand a whole day vpon his proteſtings: another ſhewes his ringes, playes with his miſtreſſes glooue, or prayſes her apparell, and prooues himſelfe a very ſotte when all is doone: but if they attayne to more priuate ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhing, that I meddle not withall, let them there doe their deuoire as they may, and let their miſtreſſes then cenſure of their deſeruing.</p>
            <p>As for their diſcourſing together, it is to detract one heere, and prayſe another there, to commend one maydens perfections, &amp; condemne the demeanour of another: ſo that were their amorous orations well liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:15023:68"/>vnto, we would greatly lament their wonderfull indiſcretion.</p>
            <p>I haue beene in place among wiſe and reuerend perſons where I haue noted good diſcourſe hath bene broken off, by ſuch as entercourſed in this idle manner, mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſcorning, when better behauiour ſhould be vſed.</p>
            <p>One beginnes, and takes his miſtreſſe by the hand, to count how many ringes ſhe hath on her fingers, talking of ſome place where he ſawe her in former tyme, requeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting renewing of olde acquaintaunce: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of other matters, ſuch as beſt is fitting their humoures: then beginnes the confuſion of ciuilitie, the thawe of modeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuch things conferd on, that might better beſeeme ſilence. Ye ſhall haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who fayne would entertayne the tyme with ſome honourable diſcourſe, ſuch as deſerueth to bee heedefully regarded: and he is hindred by anothers vayne dalliaunce, that neuer is ſatiſfied in his fonde beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niour, making no ſpare of place or
<pb facs="tcp:15023:69"/>companie, but euerie where diſcouering his follie and ſimpleneſſe. Another comes in haſt, and he hath ſome ſecret to diſcloſe, which makes the women flock about him immediately: &amp; what is this ſecret? but that is admitted into ſuch a Ladies fauour, and hath receiued ſuch and ſuch inſtaunces of her kindneſſe towarde him.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe coy wantons, haue their onely delight in walking abroad with a ſtately pace, lending their eyes about on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſide, to marke who notes them: and I know no other reaſon they haue for this behauiour, but that their fine feete might be gazed at, their gay lookes commended, and their braue apparell prayſed.</p>
            <p>If they ſtandat home in their doers &amp; haue any of like diſpoſition to acompany them: they will ſeeme as if they talked on ſome very weightie matter: when eyther it is of their pryde, or quipping and girding ſuch as paſſe by them, and no man or woman can goe along the ſtreete, but they are ſtill prepared for their gecks and tauntings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:69"/>
            <p>Others there be of a different nature, that pretending loue to men, yet coole when they ſhould kindle them: and kindle when they ſhould coole them: one while they giue them ſo good lookes, as no one can deſire better, then (in meere deſpight) they will ſtare ſo ſtraungely, as if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeene them before, counterfciting their deuiſes ſo cunningly, one while ſo lothe, then agayne ſo forwarde: as if they were to treate on a peace betweene two nations, as heeretofore our auncient women of the <hi>Gaules</hi> did, who eemed not ſo ſlacke in a caſe of importaunce, as our women (at this preſent) in thinges of no value at all.</p>
            <p>And one ſtorie of their valour I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tnet to alleadge, to ſtirre vp and encite our dames at this day to immitate them, and contrariewiſe, to ſhun and flye all wordly vanities, and heere will I ſetit downe breef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in writing, as I haue heertofore read it in the Romane hiſtories.</p>
            <p>Before the <hi>Gaules</hi> paſſed the mountaines
<pb facs="tcp:15023:70"/>of the <hi>Alpes</hi> continuing in thoſe partes of <hi>Italie</hi> where they had long remayned, there happened ſuch a great and violent ſedition among them: that at length it extended to ciuill warre.</p>
            <p>But what then did theſe generous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Gaule?</hi> euen as the two armies were meeting together, they ſtept in betweene them, and taking their cauſe of difference in hand, they cenſured thereon with ſo great equitie, and ſo well to the liking of eyther ſide: that it procured looue and good will naturally betweene Cittie and Cittie, houſe and houſe, as ſince then, they haue held an eſpeciall authoritie, not onely well thought on by their huſbandes, but likewiſe allowed in the iudgement of ſtraungers.</p>
            <p>I could eaſily recite many other examples, concerning the continencie and modeſtie of the auncient dames of <hi>Gaule,</hi> and other ſtraungers: were it not I ſtand in feare, that diuers now liuing would be diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therewith, becauſe (to their ſhame)
<pb facs="tcp:15023:70"/>they went ſo farre beyond them in all the partes of vertue, as in modeſtie, ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and chaſtitie, yea, they haue beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded by very pagan women, who had no knowledge at all of the truth. For I know very well, that the moſt of our women of theſe times, couet nothing more then to be flattered: ſo that to vſe ſpeache agreeable with their lyking, it muſt bein comparing them to Courtiers and their betters, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring their vertues, though they haue iuſt none at all, or deſpiſing others in regard of their ſingularitie. And if queſtion be made of entrance into their diſcourſings, why then it is a demaunding of ſome newes: ſuch a one is to be maryed: ſuch a one hath giuen chaynes and iewelles to his miſtreſſe: She is very gallant: ſhe hath ſuch a new faſhioned garment, with other ſuch like peeuiſh pratling, which yet they account as excellent, and meete to be compared with <hi>Appollos Oracles,</hi> becauſe therme conſters their onely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:71"/>
            <p>But when any Lady or Gentlewoman happens to be thus ſolicited, let me aduiſe them, as I would doe all other, by the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and vertuous anſwere of <hi>Gorgia</hi> daughter to <hi>Cleomenes</hi> King of <hi>Sparta,</hi> who when a ſtraunge courtier, tripping before her ſoftly and delicately, came and offered to imbrace her: ſhe rudely thruſt him away ſaying: <hi>Back bold ſir, knoweſt thou not the worth of a womans credit?</hi> this example is ſufficient for vertuous women, to repulſe the effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate follies of men.</p>
            <p>But men of good mindes deſpiſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſo ouer familiarly with any, reſpecting aſwel their quallitie, as their honor and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie: remembring withall, that baſhfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe forbids anſweres to vnſeemely que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, &amp; commonly, the inward diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is witneſſed by our woordes.</p>
            <p>Yet will I not denye, but there may paſſe ſpeeches both merrily and modeſtly, ſuch as a chaſt care may heare, and anſwere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence.</p>
            <p>VVhich if men on their behalfe would
<pb facs="tcp:15023:71"/>be more familiare withall: they ſhould finde women not ſo curious and ſtraunge, when they breake the yee to them of their amorous pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:72"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15023:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
